Good afternoon and
>> there we go.
>> Good afternoon. There we go. Welcome to
the May 18th, 2026 Public Service
Committee. Please turn off or silence
your cell phones and mute your devices
if you're online. Um to make a public
comment online, please ra use the raised
hand function. To make a public comment
in person, please um come to the podium
either side. Um turn on the green button
and if you would give us your name and
what ward you're in, that would be
great.
Um, comments must be specific to the
agenda item and we're going to limit it
to three minutes, which is customary
just because I want to make sure
everybody has an opportunity to speak.
Upon completion of the agenda items,
there'll be no further business
discussed.
And um will the clerk please Oh, I also
want to say the timers will be up on
both screens so you can see when you're
at the podium how much time you have. Um
will the clerk please read the first
agenda item?
>> Madam Chairman,
>> yes, Mr. Dr. Renick,
>> I would move to suspend the rules in
order to change the order.
>> Second.
And madam chairman, I would like to move
item 16 to the end of the agenda because
we have two short items after that. I'm
anticipating a lot of discussion on item
16. So I'd kind of like to let our staff
involved in those other items get back
to work. Hence the reason for requesting
the change in order.
And it it's a non-debatable motion and
it requires the twothirds majority which
means it requires both of us.
>> So any discussion?
>> It's non-debatable.
>> Oh, sorry. Okay. All those in favor of
moving
item number 16.
Uh please signify by saying I.
>> I. I.
>> And those opposed. Okay. So we'll move
item 16 back down to the end.
Item number seven, ordinance third
reading, amending section 13.20.050,
general prohibitions and section
13.20.070
local limits of chapter 13.20 wastewater
treatment and disposal of the code of
the city of Cheyenne, Wyoming to revise
local discharge limits and related
provisions in compliance with NPDES
and WPDEES permit requirements. Okay. Do
we have a staff report?
>> Yes, chairman, council members of the
Matt Bul trying board of public
utilities water recognition division
manager. I would make a request to amend
to postpone until the June 1. Um, we're
still under public comment through EPA
and received any public comment thus
far, but this will get us through in the
next one. We should be able to do on
third and final reading. Happy to answer
any questions.
Okay.
>> Do we have questions for staff? Dr.
Alder,
>> I'm sorry. I just didn't hear that date.
>> Uh June 1.
>> June 1.
>> Any other questions? Okay. Is there um
any public comment either online or in
the house regarding this item?
Okay. Hearing none.
>> So move and move to June 1st.
>> Oh, I would move to adopt.
So, we have a motion from Dr. Aldridge
to adopt on third reading.
>> Second,
>> and a second by Dr. um Renie.
>> Now, I would move to approve or move to
amend or to Oh my gosh.
>> Yes.
>> To postpone until June 1st.
>> Second.
>> Okay. We have a motion by Dr. Renie and
a second by Dr. I mean by Dr. Aldrich,
second by Dr. Renie to uh postpone.
All those in. Is there any discussion?
>> Public comment.
>> Okay. Any public comment?
Okay. Hearing none. Any comment from the
committee?
Okay. All those in favor please signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
Okay. So,
uh, the recommendation from the public
service committee will be to approve at
the, uh, next meeting of the governing
board. Next item,
>> Madam Chairman, the recommendation will
be to postpone.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. Okay. Just being sure. Uh number
12, ordinance, second reading, amending
the official zoning map of the city of
Cheyenne, changing the zoning
classification for land located
southwest of the intersection of HR
Ranch Road and Judy Lee Drive and
southeast of HR Ranch Road and Judy Lee
Drive from JL Ranch PUD planned unit
development to NR2 neighborhood
residential medium density.
a staff report.
Oh,
I don't know why it's doing that.
You guys have your maps in front of you.
We'll just not do that today then.
That's not necessary.
Okay, Madame Chair, members of the
committee, Morgan Dennis, Planning and
Development. This is a zone change for
about 6.77 acres located southwest of HR
Ranch Road and Judy Lee Drive and one
parcel southeast of HR Ranch Road and
Judy Lee Drive. The land is currently
vacant. The future land use map
designates this area as mixeduse
residential. This designation primarily
supports high density residential
development with a secondary focus on
commercial uses that would be supported
of the neighborhood. Uh surrounding
zoning is CBLI and HI. These zones
support the development of commercial
and industrial uses. Um this would be
isolating the NR2 zone to this area. Um
par the parcels are currently zoned the
JL Ranch PUD. This PUD was adopted in
2006 and amended in 2018 mean 20
in 2008
prior to the adoption of the UDC.
Aspects of this PUD are similar to the
NR2 zone district resulting in minimal
impact on the existing surrounding
properties. The existing lot sizes are
permitted within the NR2 zone district.
The depth of the lots would require the
applicant to seek an administrative
adjustment to for the rear setbacks.
Staff has heard from the rep from the
public regarding the zone change. One
caller was fine with the zone change.
One caller would prefer if the parcels
remained within the PUD. Planning
commission heard this on May 4th and
recommends approval. And I stand for
questions.
>> Questions for Morgan.
Okay, hearing none.
Are there Let's open it up for public
comment. Is there anybody in the room or
online that would like to comment on
this issue?
No. Oh,
>> hi. I'm And do I'm not sure what ward
I'm in, but I do have a question. Why
this push for high density housing all
over?
Um the roads I don't think are set up to
support highdensity traffic.
Um businesses aren't set up for high
density. Why this push for highdensity
housing, high density
caregiving? High density. Highdensity.
High density. So I'm really curious. I
know it's not just here. it is all over
and um I'm curious as to what you have
to say about that. Okay.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other comments?
Okay.
Hearing none,
let's move on to the committee.
And I get a motion.
Move
>> to approve on third reading.
Second.
>> Okay, we Dr. Rey move to approve on
third reading.
>> Pardon me, madam.
>> Second reading.
>> Second reading. Thank you.
>> Um Dr. Aldridge seconded. Any discussion
from the committee?
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh I did have a question. When I look at
this um proposed map and I'm just
wondering if uh the developer is online,
I don't see him or if someone knows how
wide are these lot widths. They look
like they're similar to what is in the
existing
residential area.
Chair, members of this committee, Connor
White, Planning Development Department.
I can actually answer that for you. Um,
as I've taken a look at a lot of these
lots. Um, so all the lots basically this
is just the vacant half of the
subdivision. So they all match what's
already platted out there. Um,
the NR2 is very similar to the PUD as
is. Um, it basically requires rear
loading. That's what the PUD has. That's
what a lot of the lots already um have
is rear loaded access. basically no
front loading unless they absolutely
have to have front loading because
there's some front-loaded lots out there
because they don't have an alley. Um,
but lot width I want to say is around
maybe between 40 and 50 ft wide. Uh,
which is the smaller lots, but it is all
the same throughout that entire
subdivision. Uh, that is something that
the NR2 also
kind of looks at is those smaller lot
sizes. Um,
so it isn't it isn't really changing the
development pattern out there uh with
this zone change.
>> Uh, just as a follow-up question, um,
Chairwoman Emmens, um, I'm just hopeful
that, uh, Mr. White can maybe um address
the question that was brought forth by
an from our that's in the audience today
about why we're seeing more and more um
of the medium and high density um
projects
>> uh chair through you. So when it comes
to the medium and high density um we've
gotten a lot of builders that are coming
to us wanting to look for smaller lots.
Um it makes it so that can become more
affordable. The smaller the lot is, the
smaller the home does allow for the
density. Um, as everybody knows,
Cheyenne is growing. We do have a
housing shortage. So,
we got to find places to put the
population somewhere. So, we do have
developers that have come forward
looking and requesting these um kind of
different zone districts that allow for
higher density. Again, with this
specific one, um it's not changing the
density. It's not changing how many lots
are there or anything like that. It's
basically getting it from a PUD into
standard zoning. Um, you'll see actually
we have a plat later on that is
proposing 194 lots uh with I believe 184
of those being single family residential
which is in uh neighborhood highdensity
residential zone or NR3 that was
approved by this governing body
maybe about a month ago. So that's what
we're seeing in our department. Um, it's
builders wanting to do smaller lots.
They're finding those are easier to
build. Those are what that's what's
selling here in the community. Um,
builders might be able to speak that to
that a little bit more than I could as
they're the ones bringing that to us to
then review and bring that forward.
>> Just one more followup. Sorry. Go ahead.
>> Uh, Chairwoman for you. So, I just want
to make sure that we address this that
um we're not talking about changing from
single family homes in this particular
area to for in instance apartment
buildings or an apartment complex. This
is going to be very similar to what we
see out there right now.
>> And chair through you. Uh yes. So,
basically this specific zone change is
not changing it from being single
family. Um, a lot of it just has to do
with getting out of the PUD and those
PUD standards to have city standard
zoning for uh different allowances when
it comes to building on the lots.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. Any other comments from the
committee? Dr. Renie,
>> Madame Chairman, I I just want to follow
up on that. I know Connor addressed it
pretty well, but for the public to
understand this area had been in a land
unit development. Plan unit developments
have their own rules, their own
standards. Um, and the developer in this
case wants to take it out of the plan
unit development, just use the city's
normal rules and standards for an area.
Um, so as my colleague from W three
pointed out, nothing's actually going to
change in the area. Um and the other
trying to address the the question given
to us having sat up here for a long time
I've we find that developers bring to us
what is selling or what the what the
need is at the moment and several years
ago it was single family residences. The
last few years it's been town homes and
recently it's been apartments. So it's
it's wherever there they think there we
are lacking in the way of housing that
seems to be what we get coming to us.
>> Okay. Any other discussion?
All right. Um so we have a a motion and
a second. All those in favor please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed.
Okay. So that passes
an unanimously not anonymously.
Um
So,
a recommendation from the public service
committee will be to approve um on uh at
the next meeting of the governing board.
Next item, number 14, ordinance, second
reading, amending the official zoning
map of the city of Cheyenne, changing
the zoning classification for land
located in Cheyenne Business Park and
Camp Stool Business Park and Eastern
Cheyenne along I80 from LI Light
Industrial, HIV Industrial, and CB
Community Business to BP Business Park.
>> Okay. Staff report.
>> Chair, members of the committee, Conor
Planning and Development Department. So
the zone change before you, it's
actually a city initiated zone change.
Uh so this is staff basically bringing
this forward um and proposing this. Uh
we did have a council work session to
kind of bring up looking at various
parts of the city to do city initiated
zone changes. One of the ones we
definitely want to start with was um
some business parks and get them into
our business park zone district that had
been adopted and created. So before you
is looking at Cheyenne Business Park and
Camptool Business Park. Uh this is over
on the eastern side of Cheyenne. It's
all zoned either HI Li or CB which is
our community business zone district. Um
so the zone change basically proposes
changing much of that area to our
business park zone district.
with uh the zone change. The reason
staff is the one bringing this this
forward is trying to get every property
owner together to sign off on an
application to get the 320 acres
required for a for the BP zone can be
very challenging. Um so
staff is that's why staff is bringing
this forward. Uh we did mail all
property owners so they were mailed
ahead of time and were basically
informed that the zone change is being
brought forward by staff. Uh we also had
to mail to all property owners within
300 feet about the zone change.
Um
we have been contacted by property
owners. Um
most of the questions that those
property owners within the zone change
had were kind of what does this do for
my property? What are the differences
between what I currently have and what
this would change? We did provide all
that information to them. Um most are
basically completely fine with it. We
did have one property owner who did
request to be removed. Um, and Dr.
Aldrich, you might um be happy to hear,
but we did actually remove them. Um, so
if we do have a property owner that has
requested to be removed, uh, we have
removed them from the zone change. Um,
we're not making it mandatory. If
somebody wants to be out, they can be
out. So, what we did at planning
commission, we did have the motion. We
did have them remove it. So, the
ordinance in front of you has those
properties removed. Um, if through this
council process, if a property owner
comes in and asks to be removed, staff
would probably recommend that you do
remove them. Um, we're not trying to
force people who don't want to be part
of the zone change to be a part of it.
Uh, it's staff basically looking at the
area and basically making it a little
bit easier when it comes to uses that
are already allowed in the zone
districts. Um the BP zone is a mix of
our HI LI and CB zone. So out in this
area we actually have had parcels where
they started as CB, they got reszone to
LI, project didn't happen, they got
resoneed back to CB. So that is months
of applicants having to reszone back and
forth just to get their project uh to
move forward.
Again, the BP zone is basically already
a combination of the LIHI and CB zone,
which is what is out in this area. Um,
haven't had any other comments from
neighboring properties and I haven't had
any comments from property owners since
the ones I've talked to are since
planning commission. Um, planning
commission did recommend approval. Uh,
staff does recommend approval. I'm also
available for any questions. Okay.
>> Thank you, Connor. Any questions for
staff?
Dr. Aldrich.
>> Thank you, Chairwoman Emmensu. Um, I see
the letter here from the business owner
that wanted to be removed and they're
currently zoned according to this letter
as heavy industrial and we were wanting
to take them to business park. Um,
and thank you for including the uh other
uh businesses and entities that are
included in this change. Can you um just
tell me what are the
what items or what could they do under
heavy industrial that they cannot do
under business park? Would it be
primarily uh heavy manufacturing for
instance?
>> Share through you. So one of the things
the the reason that they wanted to be
out of it is in the business park zone
district we don't allow outdoor storage
like a full complete outdoor storage of
a lot. You can have limited outdoor
storage. So less than 50% of your lot
can be used as outdoor storage, but they
wanted to have the ability cuz it sounds
like they're looking to sell that
property. So they wanted to have that
marketable ability to say you can use
this as outdoor storage fully cuz most
of it isn't really developed. It was a
RV sales lot. So a good portion is just
fenced in and has nothing on it. So that
does make it kind of easy and useful.
Um, I will say for any I did have a
conversation with a business that does
have outdoor storage as a use on their
property. Um, they basically become
legal non-conforming. So, we still allow
it. Uh, they just can't expand it
without getting a conditional use. But
the property that I'm talking about and
the property owner I talked with, they
don't really have anywhere to expand.
So, they're fine with going to the BP
zone because it doesn't really it's not
changing their operation. It's not
changing how they can use the property
already. Um but specifically for that
one they just want that marketable
ability in the hi uh that they have with
the outdoor storage component.
>> Okay. Any other questions from
committee?
>> Okay.
Uh public comment are is there any
public comment either online or in the
room regarding this issue or this item?
Hello. Hi, Heather Madrid, Ward One. My
mine is more of a question. Um, my
understanding, and I might be wrong
here, please correct me, but is that
once it is a business park that whatever
happens on the business park is none of
our business anymore. Is that correct?
Honor, would you like to speak to that,
please?
shared through you. Um, no. Basically,
this is just the zone district that kind
of controls the uses, but it has nothing
to do with the actual definition or what
kind of is considered the business park.
It's just the zoning for it. So, the
uses, the land uses, the design
requirements, the standards.
>> Madam Chairman,
>> yes,
>> Mr. Why if something is going if a
business is going into an appropriate
zone,
it doesn't come back through this body.
It's just approved administratively.
Correct. Chair through you. That would
be correct. So, if it is a permitted use
in the zone district, then it's
administrative. Um, we do post projects
on our Connect Cheyenne website. Um, but
otherwise, it's if it's a permitted use,
it goes through the administrative
review process for site plans. If it
requires a conditional use or anything
like that, then that would go to board
of adjustment
>> and would go through a public process.
>> As a followup, if something is already
um zoned HI or LII,
essentially the same uses are going to
be permitted in a business zone. I mean,
it it's not more lenient than what they
currently have as LI or HI. Correct.
>> M truth through you. When it comes to
uses
because it's a combination of the three.
Yes, BP allows maybe more flexibility on
certain uses when it comes to commercial
aspects that maybe the HI doesn't, but
it's not. If the question is does this
basically allow data centers more
easily? No,
the LIHI and CB zones allow for those
already. So, this does not change that.
That was my point. Thank you.
>> Go ahead.
>> Hi, Michael Larson. Um, and I'm a little
confused if uh they're already already
allowed to have a data center in this
area, will that be subject or to any
kind of uh industrial site council act
review of uh any kind of proposed data
center there?
>> Madam Chair, through you uh that I have
no idea when it comes to the industrial
sighting committee. That's not something
that I'm involved in.
>> In other words, I'm I understand that by
designating or reszoning areas to
business parks or industrial parks,
there is no need to go through the uh
state um industrial site act to uh
review any kind of application.
So madam chair through you these areas
are already designated as business parks
this is again this is just zoning this
is the city zoning code the z city
zoning regulations what uses are allowed
what design standards what criteria that
they have to follow when building on a
property when it comes to the industrial
sighting I I don't think they take into
account the zone district I think they
take into account if something is
classified by leads as a business park
but not from the zoning code but that
I'm again my department doesn't deal
with industrial sighting committee or
anything.
>> Thank you Connor. I would ask that if
you've got questions specific to the
data center issue let's wait till we get
to item 16 so that we don't get things
conflated.
Um
>> sorry
>> Heather Madrid. Um I mean it is data
center related but my concern is that
this will just this particular item is
going to move forward and be approved
and then
it is what it is at that point. And so
I'm just trying to understand if it
already is business park why do we what
why do we have to change it? I don't
understand the need for the change if it
already is
business park.
Charles
Go ahead, Councilman Lelay.
>> Thank you. Um, I think this is in a way
relevant to this discussion here. I know
that when we look at uh those changes in
the state and the uh industrial
sighting, um, we need an explanation. I
think it'd be really good to have one
right here right now. how that changes
because we have before us a uh action
with some of the windmills up north that
fall under the industrial sighting act
and thereby offer uh various um
communications and assistance to the
city as a result of that development.
However, at the present time, uh what it
what it has occurred and what I think
there are a lot of people in the
audience that are probably interested in
is when those uh data centers are placed
in an existing business park, which is
there are some out in this business park
right now. And so it that's uh part of
it, but that does exclude that
industrial sighting commission action.
And I think that uh maybe we can get an
explanation of that. I although it I
believe it's relevant to this discussion
before us because certainly there is a
possibility that uh there are there are
business parks out in that area. This is
a adoption of a more comprehensive
uh look at our business parks in
general. So um I think an explanation
would be in order. Madam Chairman,
>> Director Bloom, would you like to weigh
in on this?
>> Chair, members of public service
committee, Charles Bloom, planning and
development director. I'm just want to
note this is a a zone change. Um, right
now, majority of the area is zoned
industrial zone district. This is zoning
to BP. There have been discussion on the
changes of land uses and uh Connor
White, he had mentioned that there are
this is a blend of different zone
districts. what the true impetus of this
zone change is is to recognize um the
type of development that's going on in
that area, which is light industrial
development, and make sure the
improvements are balanced with that type
of development. Um if you go to the the
area, um there are predominantly
larger lots in in out west and there are
smaller lots out east. We've had
struggles with uh landscaping code and
site design and these business park zone
district standards um are more
commenurate with what's expected in the
area and they um better remove barriers
to all types of development in that area
not specifically to any use. It's for
all developments in the area.
>> Thank you Councilwoman.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> U before we move on I just have a
question for Mr. Bloom. Um, I think part
of the confusion may be um, Director
Bloom is that, um, people may not
understand that business park is
actually a zone that is very new for
this council, relatively speaking. I
mean, it hasn't always existed. And so
this is really in my my understanding of
this, this is really kind of a
housekeeping issue, if you will,
cleaning up our our zoning um codes and
business park is only been on the books
since when?
>> Go ahead,
>> chair. Through you to Dr. Aldrich. Um
you are correct. This is our most recent
zone district that we have created. Um I
believe that has been effect for just
about
about eight 18 months roughly plus or
minus a few months there. It is a newer
one and the title business park that is
a name that's not a descriptor. We have
other zone districts like community
business neighborhood business. Um
they're titled to encompass the variety
of uses that are allowed in there. In
this case, this is to um the company
accommodate variety of different
businesses.
>> Okay. Thank you. Okay. More public
comment.
>> Good afternoon committee. My name is
Dante Rushton, director of real estate
and property management for Cheyenne
Leadeds. Leadeds supports this amendment
by city staff. Um notably items such as
the water conservation efforts through
reduced landscaping via reduced trees
and just some setting some form for
formalities with the nomenclature. Yes,
this is a business park zoning district.
This is housed within the Shyen business
parkway. It's operated with a commercial
owners association and its own private
restrictive covenants. I'll stand for
any questions.
>> Thank you, Dante.
Councilman Leborn.
Okay. Any other public comment?
Okay. Is there any comment online?
Okay.
All right. Then I'm going to close
public comment.
Can I get a motion and a second?
>> I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay. I have uh Dr. Aldrich move to
approve and Dr. Renie seconded. Any
discussion from the committee?
Councilman Lebourne.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um,
I think uh we need to take a look at why
these people are here today and what
their interest is in our process.
I don't think they're familiar with uh
the various zoned issues. And so I think
it's really important that um and I'm
just speculating, but I'm pretty
confident that we're going to hear some
comments shortly here that we don't
listen. That is a constant
drum beatat of people's opinion on this
matter in particular, but other matters
as well. And I think that it's not out
of order, Miss Madame Chairman, for an
individual to come up and ask a specific
question that uh doesn't relate directly
to the zoning of this particular site,
but very much relates to the overall
issue that these people are here about.
They they want to know how
their community, how their county, how
their city deals with zoning parks and
their relationship to their exclusion
from the Industrial Sighting Act. And
I'm I'm disappointed we didn't hear
that. But uh I hope the issue's been
raised and maybe we can uh deal with
that as we go ahead because it it is a
substantial and fundamental issue of
this whole question. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Is there any other discussion
from the committee?
If not, all those Oh, sorry, Dr. Renie.
I
>> just to try and give a little
background. Um
I was part of helped write the original
landscaping ordinance in the late 80s
early 90s and at that time we were
looking at landscaping along Dell Range
or Persing or Yellowstone.
We had no concept that
we would be looking at
developments whether it be business,
commercial or residential that would be
comprise a section or larger.
Um so back in so when we were writing
those ordinances we put in a lot of
buffering and landscaping between
different businesses and different
zones. And what we discovered was that
with the development of with some of
these large developments,
we were requiring
that some of them plant like Microsoft
out south had to plant a forest out on
the prairie to meet our landscaping
requirements.
That didn't make a lot of sense. So the
business park zone was was done
specifically to address those large
projects. they can have the same uses
that they're getting in light
industrial, heavy industrial, but we did
scale back the landscaping requirements
for something like that to be much more
reasonable. So, that is one of the
biggest changes
um and probably one of the biggest
drivers to change this to a business
park zone. Thank you.
>> Any other discussion?
Okay, hearing none. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed. Okay. So, the re
recommendation from the public service
committee will be to approve at the next
governing board meeting.
Next agenda item,
>> item number 26, resolution authorizing
the mayor and the city clerk to sign a
final plat for Polo Properties, City of
Cheyenne, Larry County, Wyoming, located
south of East 12th Street, east of Crest
Park Drive and west of Cottonwood Drive.
Staff report. Madame Chair, members of
the committee, Morgan Dennis, Planning
and Development.
This is an expedited plat for 1.42 acres
of land. Um the lot is currently vacant.
The purpose of this plat is to vacate 10
lots and the existing culde-sac to
create a common lot and individual lots
for the buildings.
Uh the responsibility of maintenance for
the common lot will be split amongst
each building owner. Uh they will
they will be responsible for maintaining
the common lot to the approved site
plan. The site plan is currently
undergoing review process within our
department. Uh the future land use map
designates this area as urban
residential. The zoning for this parcel
is MR, which is medium density
residential. Um multi-dwelling buildings
are conditional use within the MR zone.
This parcel received approval for
multi-dwelling buildings from the board
of adjustment in August of 2025.
Um, this allows all lot types allow to
be allowable within the MR zone
district.
Um, the lots proposed are reflective of
the building buildings on the approved
site plan and are buildable in the MR
zone. Planning commission heard this on
May 4th and recommends approval. I stand
for questions.
>> Any questions? Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, Chairwoman Emmens through you. Uh, I
have to say I I lived like four or five
blocks from this area and I don't I'm
not remembering an empty lot there, so I
I must be well hidden by trees and
things um to the south of 12th Street.
But I'm curious on the diagram that
we've been given, it shows that it looks
like these are going to be I'm guessing
they look like probably twin homes or
forplexes or something based on the
parking layout that we've been provided.
Uh, Madam Chairman, through you. Um,
yes, I believe they are forplexes. Um,
the applicant is here and he can expand
on it. Okay. If you wish,
>> that would be great. I And I just had a
question about I'm not sure what the big
empty space is
at the opening of the sub of this little
culde-sac. if that's just a green green
space with a driveway on either side of
it or and I'm sorry that you can't
evidently show this. So,
>> my laptop is deciding to restart. So, I
am so sorry.
>> Technology is amazing when it works.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. I do apologize greatly.
>> Thank you. Is the developer here? Yes,
>> Madam Chair through you John Sers's
agent for True Grit and Casa CE
Investments. So to answer your question,
Dr. Aldridge, it is a forplex complex.
We did receive conditional use of that
property. It is vacant in that area. Um
there is houses surrounding that area
and we have gone in and done the
conditional use to go ahead and get the
multif family approved on that. um when
acquiring that process or that property
and looking at it, we can't get lots to
fit with the size of the road in there.
So, we do have a buyer that is
considering this project for us. Um with
that in mind, we do have eight forplexes
and one common space. The common space
will have a each individual building
will have a 1/8 interest or yeah 1/8
interest into lot nine to remedy that
situation. So, the tax situation's
covered and and the basis is there. Um
the front piece that you were talking
about is two access or ingress egress,
but that middle space acts as a
detention pond area.
>> Okay.
>> For that. So it'll it'll have a dog park
basically in on the inside of that plus
it'll have the detention and then we're
working with city staff for some
potential offsite just because the the
volume of water over in that particular
area and not having five and seven foot
walls over there. So we've been working
with engineering at this point. Happy to
address any other questions. Other
questions for Mr. Sers?
>> Okay. Thank you.
Is there any public comment about this
issue or this item? Mr. White.
>> Madame Chairman, uh, Michael White,
Larry County. Um, I have a question for
the council.
The information that you just received
from the people from the planning
department,
was that available before this meeting
started to the public?
>> Go ahead, Connor.
>> Madam Chair, through you. Yes, this plat
did go to planning commission. Went to
planning commission on May 4th. that was
posted on our planning commission's web
page a week before that meeting and it
has been there since. Uh this plat has
also been posted on connect Cheyenne
which is also available to the public to
log in and look at various projects. So
this this project has been and it also
went to the board of adjustment for
conditional use approval which also had
mailed notice and also on the board of
adjustments web page. So this project
itself has actually been available to
the public um for quite a few months.
Uh follow-up question, Madame Chairman.
So, in other words, if if the
information that we were in involved
with today, we get on the city council
website for the public service
commission, that information would have
been part of this agenda today. Is that
correct,
>> Madam Chairwoman? Yes, it would have
been posted I I believe I had everything
posted last Wednesday before the end of
the day for sure.
>> Thank you, Jennifer.
Thank you. Any other public comment?
Is there any public comment online?
Okay.
Sorry.
>> Okay. Thank you. So, I'll close public
comment. Can I get a motion and a
second?
>> Move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Okay. Dr. Dr. Aldrich moved to approve
and Councilman Lelaybornne seconded. Any
discussion from the committee?
Dr. Aldridge. Oh, okay.
Okay. Hearing none. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> And those opposed. Okay. The
recommendation from the public service
committee will be to adopt at the next
meeting of the governing board.
Number 20. Number 27. Resolution
authorizing the mayor and the city clerk
to sign a final plat for Darnell home
site. Second filing, city of Cheyenne,
Larmy County, Wyoming, located west of
Bridge Road and east of Darnell Place.
Staff report.
Madame Chairman, members of the
committee, Morgan Dennis, Planning and
Development. Um, this is an expedited
plat for 1.02 acres of land. The lot
currently has um a vacant ra residential
structure on half of the parcel and is
vacant on the rest of it. The purpose of
this plot is to subdivide this one lot
into five lots for residential use. The
future land use map designates this area
as mixeduse residential. The zoning for
this parcel is MR medium density
residential.
The lots facing Darnell Place are 0.6 6
ft short of the standard for the DD7 lot
type. This is 1.5%
of the required 40 ft of frontage. This
front this frontage is smaller when
compared to the frontage in the
immediate area. However, the overall lot
area is similar is similar when compared
to lots in the immediate area.
The remaining lot facing ridge road
would be considered DD5 in the MR zone
district. Initially there was a
condition attached to this plat the
board of public utilities was asking for
a water utility easement on the map. Um
since then that has been resolved
between OPU and the applicant. Um it can
continue with the condition throughout
this entire process and it won't affect
the final the final product. Um,
planning commission heard this on May
4th and is recommending approval and I
stand for questions.
>> Any questions for staff? Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, Chairwoman Amens through you. Um,
Morgan, have we had any public comment
on this?
>> Uh, Madam Chairman, through you. No, we
have not received any public comment.
>> And one more followup question. I for
the people that are here today and for
those that are watching online
>> um when you say an expedited request um
that by no means circumvents or um
eliminates opportunity for public
comment. Is that correct?
>> U Madame Chairman through uh no ma'am.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay. Any other questions?
Okay.
Um, then we'll go to public comment. Is
there any comment in the room or online?
Okay. I can't tell if people are coming
up. We're just moving around. Okay. Um,
hearing no public comment, we'll move
on. Um, can I get a motion and a second?
>> Move to adopt.
>> Second.
>> Dr. Renie moved to adopt and Dr. Aldrich
seconded. Any discussion from the
committee?
Okay. Hearing none. All those in favor,
please signify by saying I. I.
>> And all those opposed.
All right. So, the recommendation from
the public service committee will be to
adopt at the next meeting of the
governing board. Number 28. Resolution
authorizing the mayor and city clerk to
sign a final plat for Harmony Valley
23rd filing city of Cheyenne Larmy
County, Wyoming, located south of West
Allison Road, west of Waltershy
Boulevard and north of West College
Drive.
Staff report
chair and members of the committee
planning and development department. Uh
so this is actually the plot that I had
referenced earlier when it comes to kind
of one of the larger subdivisions that
uh we've had come uh to our office
recently.
So this is over by Harmony Valley. It is
south of uh West Allison is north of
College.
The applicant is proposing replatting
these uh there's two couple large
parcels out here. They're looking at
replanting that uh 49.56
acres of land into roughly 196 lots.
About 184 of them will be for single
family residential. Um they're with this
uh plat they are going to use the
cottage lot section of our zoning code
which allows for smaller lots. Um front
doors basically face open space, green
area uh for a good chunk of them. Others
do face the street, but everything is
rear loaded. So, there are alleys
proposed with this plat um as well as
your standard streets.
This is actually a continuation of
Harmony Valley fifth filing which was
approved by the governing body just to
the west. Uh similar style of product,
similar design um
and also has open space elements. There
are 12 open space lots uh proposed with
this plat. Um as a reminder again, this
area was reszone to NR3 by this
governing body. Um which does allow uh
for kind of the denser development, but
again with our NR zones, it does require
the rear loaded access uh which is why
alleys are provided with this.
There are major road connections being
provided. So, Grand Harmony, I think
it's Grand Harmony Circle on the east,
connects down from College all the way
up to um Allison
at the north.
Um and then everything connects into
York on the west side.
There is no connection into the
subdivision
to the east. um where there could be a
possible connection as extraordinarily
uh steep slope. Uh the applicant is
investigating putting in a pedestrian
connection uh as long as engineering
kind of works out depending on ADA um
access and stuff with with their slopes.
I'm sure the applicant can uh touch on
that a little bit more, but there is I
believe it's Melody Loop um has a dead
end from that uh development to the east
that would dead end basically
um let me go actually on the map I can
try to highlight it.
So it's right in this area
uh melody loop kind of dead ends.
We would expect to have a street there,
but due to grades, it'd be
extraordinarily difficult to get a road
connection. That's why I mentioned the
applicant is looking at a potential
pedestrian connection uh to kind of link
the neighborhoods.
So that is why with the um staff's
recommendation for approval, there is
the condition
um in there that a pedestrian access or
pedestrian easement be provided uh prior
to signing of the plat or with another
instrument if basically the engineering
works out. um if the engineering doesn't
work out and
um it's basically determined that a
connection isn't really feasible, that
basically still allow them to submit the
plat and get it recorded uh just without
that easement. So other than that, we do
have the exception to block size. These
are larger than your typical blocks, but
they are broken up by open space. Um, so
that's why staff does recommend the
exception to block size because it's not
just straight uh straight blocks with um
homes basically around the entire block
face. You do have open space that breaks
up those block sizes as well as alleys.
Planning commission did hear this item.
Uh they did recommend approval and
staff does recommend approval and I'm
available for any questions.
>> Any questions for Mr. White? Dr.
Aldridge,
>> Chairwoman Emmens throughu, have you had
any public comments or anyone reach out
to your office based on the this
information?
>> Chair throughu. Uh, no. Our department
hasn't had um any comments. Uh, back
when it was being reszoned, there were
some comments just about traffic and
things like that, but there was nothing
at the platting stage.
>> Okay. Would the developer like to speak
about this?
Madame Chair, John Sers, agent for True
Grit Land Development. So when we
started working on Harmony Valley Fifth
Filing, this was the next extension
piece. We've taken it out of the PUD, we
reszoneed it to NR3 requirements. Um, as
the affordability level keeps rising in
Cheyenne, trying to build an affordable
product. uh it's the smaller homes that
is the need for residents, not the 6,000
plus square foot lots and maintenance
and mowing and so forth. So with the
product that we offer, we're about 329
at the market price somewhere close to
there based on having an attached
dwelling at that point. And to me that's
not affordable, but unfortunately that
is where we are at. Uh with that said,
we do have uh open space. That open
space is all tied into the HOA that
actually pays for its own park over in
this area. So, the residents of the uh
Harmony Valley filing pay HOA fees about
450 a year to maintain the area. We're
just about ready to start putting the
ash turf or the sod down on the uh
football field/playfield
over off to the side and we have the
landscaping, the pickle balls and the
basketball courts up and running
compared to other sites that don't have
any parks at this point. Uh with that
said, uh initially there was comment in
the uh zone change only because they
thought we were putting higher density
residential apartments over in that
area. We are so we are doing NR3 so
there is a affordability and some type
of permanent uh capabilities for people
to buy a house at that point. The uh
Grand Harmony Boulevard will connect
from college all the way up to Allison.
that's uh connecting a major arterial to
a minor arterial and then eventually as
you can see York will tie up to Cribbon
that is a city project somewhere in the
release of 2028 to get that other
connection up. We do have pathways
getting up to the school district but as
the school district limits the
capabilities of people to directly
access certain areas. We did struggle
with that at planning commission. They
felt that school district wanted more
accesses. That's not the case. We've
been working with them. We're actually
working on that hill behind south to
remedy that, but Triumph just put a
fence along their north side. So, they
are fencing off all their project or
their uh schools, so there's not direct
access. So, we are making it to where
there will be a pathway along uh Grand
Harmony Boulevard. In regards to the
access off of Melody Loop, that's a 15%
slope in less than 100 ft. So, it's
quite challenging at this point. We are
trying to figure out how to make that
somehow adequate for access, but um the
kids have been doing it for quite a
while and cutting across illegally on
the property. So, I'm sure they'll
continue, but in regards to making it
ADA, I'm not sure how we're going to
make that happen.
>> Happy to answer any other questions.
>> Okay, questions for Mr. Sers.
Councilman Rick Leborn.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Um Mr. Sears,
there's been a discuss ongoing
discussion about South High sitting on
the ridge there above this subdivision
since it began. And one of the concerns
that I have and I think is probably
not all that unusual is how the
pedestrian connection can come from that
subdivision up to the school. Are you
telling me that the school is no longer
interested in that pedestrian
connection?
>> Madam Chair, through you, Pete, if you
go out there and take a look, you have
no openings in the fence from the tennis
courts all the way around to the far
east side to the parking lot.
>> There is no chain link open fence areas.
The only spot for access is next to the
tennis courts for Laram County School
District vehicles to get in and do
maintenance on the top side of that
hill. There is not a single fence
opening along that area. So, the kids
have been trespassing down the hillside
and coming across our property to get
back into certain areas. So, with the
access roads that we're building with
Grand Harmony Boulevard, you'll have
pedestrian access on both sides of Grand
Harmony all the way up to Allison. You
have no access of sidewalk along
Walteride, which is not our project
whatsoever. But that is why you're
seeing the kids cut through because what
portion of them don't feel safe walking
along Walteride are just cutting across
through our area.
>> I see. Um, thank you. A followup, Madam
Chairman. Um,
that's very unfortunate and is something
that uh I think we should I think the
school district should consider and I
think we should consider um if that's
what the kids are doing. Uh that's
because they see it as uh reasonable to
access the school and the facilities.
And I'm very disappointed that we can't
do that. But I understand
uh security at this point is uh
very difficult. But uh thank you for
your explanation.
>> Dr. Aldridge
Troun for you. Uh having been a longtime
educator in this school district, I can
tell you that um that is the common
model right now is to fence off schools
completely. Um part of it is because of
security, but the majority of it is
because of liability. and what happens
after hours on school property. Um, so
while I think it's unfortunate and
having been a teacher at one of those
schools that's affected by this
development, um, I think that that's
definitely the school district's
prerogative as a private property or as
a property owner. Um, and it's
unfortunate, you're right, Councilman
Labour, that um, they don't have the
students don't have access on that
backside. um it means they have to walk
a little bit further and you know
literally uphill both ways in a
snowstorm like you know the rest of us
had to walk to school evidently um but I
I think it is um based on what's best in
the best interest of students and
faculty and staff at those facilities um
for security purposes.
>> Thank you Mr. Sers.
Okay, is there any public comment either
in the room or online?
Thank you, Councilwoman. Chairwoman, my
name is Patricia McCoy. I live on the
south side. I'm a county resident.
I got to be honest with you. When I
found out that we were putting in all of
this housing, I thought to myself, why?
What for? We already can't get to the
schools. We already can't get our kids
from school. You get traffic backed up
all the way down to South Gley on
Allison because people are waiting to
get into the two loops for South and
Johnson. I know I sit in them every
morning and every afternoon. Thank god
my son's a senior this year so I get to
pick him up a little bit earlier.
You can't expand any of those roads.
There's nowhere to expand Allison.
There's nowhere to expand Fox Farm.
There's nowhere to expand Walters Road.
But everybody wants to put more housing
and more people there and say, "H,
you'll all fit in. it'll be fine. What
are we going to do about all the traffic
that's already there that we already
can't get through? What are we doing
about all the water that these people
are going to also need to use? I
appreciate Mr. Leborn saying that
there's no way for students to cut
through. My kid was one of them that
walked that hill when we had just a
house on that hill that conveniently
caught fire right before annexation
happened. It's funny how these things
just keep happening and nobody can
explain it to any of us.
My kids walked that hill. They got to
their schools just fine. There's no
sidewalk on Waltershide for the kids to
walk on. But hey, let's tell them it's
safe. Do it anyway. Don't walk down the
hill. Walk down Waltershide Boulevard.
No sidewalk. But it's okay that they do
that, right?
It's extremely frustrating as a
Southside resident for 18 years
to watch your community
build up all of this housing that's
affordable.
So affordable, guys.
Well, none of us can actually afford it.
You got all these people coming from out
of state to live here and we already
can't get around our town. This is a
small town trying to be a big town.
We're not a big town. We're a small
town. We like it being a small town.
It's why we chose to live here. We live
in the county. We live on the southside
because we like the way that we live our
lives out in our open spaces. But you
just want to fill them up with
quadplexes, duplexes. There's already a
ton of them over there. We don't need
more of those over there. There's no
reason, explanation, or excuse as to why
this housing is necessary and needed to
be right there. And when we ask
questions about the traffic, we're told,
"Oh, you'll get a roundabout at Fox Farm
and Walters. That'll help. That'll be
better than the four-way stop you have
now. That'll mitigate all the traffic
issues that you see on all of these
roads." I want someone to explain to me
why a roundabout that people don't know
how to use in this town anyway, no
offense to anyone,
why is that going to mitigate?
>> Thank you, Miss McCoy. Your time is up.
Hello, Heather Madrid. I live in Harmony
Meadows. I agree with the woman who just
spoke, but my son is also one who is
trespassing every day to get to school
because he can't safely leave the
neighborhood otherwise and get to school
on a street that is already heavily
congested and sounds like is just going
to continue to get worse. So, while I
understand it's not I can't I'm sorry I
can't remember name the responsibility
of the developer to put sidewalks in
Walter Shide whose responsibility is it?
um because our children are not safe.
And not only that, and I don't know who
the developer of the already existing
housing that's going up in that area is,
but there's been no sidewalks put on
College Drive either, where the speed
limit is 50 m hour in what is pretty
much a school zone at 50 m hour right in
front of Triumph High School and very
close to Rossman Elementary. There's no
sidewalk. So, these kids are supposed to
walk in either the mud and the muck or
in the street where it's 50 miles an
hour. Um, it's just another example of
the the
planning that is just not well thought
out. Um, I'm going to continue to
encourage my child to trespass because I
want him to come home safely from school
just the way that he gets there safely
to school. So, again, with the public
access to the schools, that's not just
like a gee, that would be nice. We want
our kids to survive the trip to and from
school. So please consider those things
when you're approving all this
development.
>> Thank you.
Other comments.
Are there any comments online?
No. Okay.
All right. Then I'm going to close down
public comment.
Um can I get a motion and a second?
I would move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Dr. Aldridge moved to approve. Uh,
Councilman Leborn seconded. Any
discussion from the committee?
>> Yes,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, Councilwoman Emmens for you. I just
wanted to say I think you know I I'm a
little frustrated quite honestly as a
council person because I hear repeatedly
that um we need more affordable
attainable housing and now we're hearing
well why are you putting in more
affordable attainable housing. Um then
we hear, you know, we need to um make
sure we diversify our economy and we
need to make sure there are jobs and
then we hear but we really don't want
people to move to our community and we
don't want those jobs and that
diversification of our economy. I I I am
just frustrated that, you know, I today
we're hearing about why isn't there a
sidewalk down Waltershide, but two
months ago we were hearing about why
would you ever think about putting a
sidewalk down Waltershide if you're, you
know, because that might impact um
someone you're planning to annex um or
hoping, you know, was up for a proposed
annexation that we'll hear again about
in September. So,
as a council person, I think we're asked
to weigh all of these things and to try
and balance those and to try and make
sure that everyone in our community is
taken care of. Um, and it's never hope I
my goal is never to have it be at the
risk of a student um trying to get to
and from school or to be at the risk of
um the quality of life that our
residents experience. Um but I think
that um please just be mindful of you
know that we are trying to balance a lot
of different people's interest. Um as I
used to say to my students a lot of
times it's not always just about you. So
thank you for engaging in this process.
Um, please know we're hearing what
you're saying, but we are trying to
balance um a lot of different demands
and requests um from a lot of different
residents um and trying to do our best
job to do that to represent you.
Okay. Any other discussion from the
committee?
Okay. So, um we have a motion and a
second. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. opposed.
Okay. The recommendation from the public
service committee will be to adopt um at
the next meeting of the governing B
board. Next item number 16, ordinance,
second reading, imposing a temporary
12-month moratorum on the establishment,
construction, or conversion of any
buildings or structures for use as a
data center, including any change of use
to a data data center.
Okay. So, I want to reiterate, we want
to hear from everybody who wants to
speak. We're going to do three minutes.
We're going to do one time through.
If there are still people after that,
then we can do that, but we're not I
don't want in order to make sure
everybody is heard, I don't want people
to come up two or three times so that
everybody can speak. Okay. The timer
will be on the screen and we are going
to maintain the or we're gonna keep this
specific to the moratorum. We're not
Whoops. We're not going broad all over
the place. So, we're going to talk about
the moratorum.
Okay. Mr. Mayor, I understand you have a
staff report.
Madame Chairman, members of the
committee, I really hadn't planned on
speaking today, but uh I do have the uh
the ordinance in front of me here and I
can speak to um uh some of the items
that are on there and uh you know, my
plans um when it got next week to the
governing body meeting. Um, and as I
read the ordinance, what it asks for is
a study on the impact of data centers on
the environment, on our electric rates,
on the power grid, on water usage, and
factors like health, safety, and welfare
of our residents. So, as I looked at
those over the last few uh days, um, and
I look at the environmental impacts and
asking staff, I don't know that I think
staff has um, the expertise to do an
environmental study. I don't know that
that's within our uh our area. When we
talk about the uh electric rates, I did
go back and look at those. Black Hills
Energy's had one rate case in the last
decade. That was in 2022. And that rate
case was uh because of some focused
investments that Black Hills Energy had
spent on infrastructure. According to
the case, there was four areas that they
were working on. uh consumer customer
reliability, the distribution system and
some of the improvements they made to
that some customer focused renewable
assets and then supporting Cheyenne's
growth. The case asked for a 1% rate
increase when inflation from 2014 which
was the last increase to 2022 was 2.5%.
Uh the expenses were not a driver in the
case but were driven by capital
investments into Cheyenne system. We got
an 8.6% 6% increase um at that time.
2014 was also the the previous case and
that was to build the Cheyenne uh the
CPGS I think it's they call it the
Cheyenne prairie generation system. Uh
that was adding uh some capacity and
reliability to our system. In 2014 when
that happened we didn't have significant
data center loads and it did not drive
that increase. And at that same time, we
had the the low the power tariff uh that
was in place uh that prevented utilities
from using uh data center capital
investments. They can't do that and pass
those on to our residents. Um it asked
about the power grid. A little research
on the power grid. Um I learned it's
really a shared responsibility. Uh
locally, Black Hills Energy is
responsible for the local distribution,
delivery of electricity to homes and
businesses. uh responsible for liability
reliability at the local level. Our high
voltage transmission lines that's shared
regionally um and a lot of coordination
goes into that. Uh Black Hills does have
some of their own transmission lines but
uh broadly it's it's a shared
responsibility. The reliability is the
North American Electric Reliability
Corporation or NERK. Federally it's FK,
Federal Energy Regulatory Commission.
They do the interstate transmission,
wholesale power markets in approval of
transmission projects. At the state
level, it's the public service
commission who approves the utility
rates, the infrastructure improvements,
and the customer reliability.
When I look at the uh the grid, I'm not
sure I see a place for the city council
in that process. It's regulated, if you
will, above our pay grade. Water usage.
We've had uh data centers in Cheyenne
since the greenhouse data opened in
2009. Larger data center started about
14 years ago when Microsoft went into
the North Range Business Park. I don't
know that we need to speculate on water
usage. We can look back in history and
um we can extrapolate that data for
future water use. We know that our
existing data centers used 200 acre feet
of water annually. That the original
data centers used an evaporative cooling
technology that were more water
intensive. Uh and all of our data
centers combined today use 1.48% of all
of our water usage uh as sold by the
board of public utilities. Uh that
technology has changed how data centers
are cooled. Instead of c cooling the
server room today uh technology cools
the chips themselves. Um that uh
technologies have reduced or eliminated
the use of water and cooling. We're
using today close loot systems which
reduce water consumption.
examples we've gotten from two data
centers currently being built are two
acre feet of water to charge the system
then that water is recirculated for up
to six years and we also have new air
cooled systems where no water is used at
all in the cooling the portable public
utilities I think has a good
understanding of water usage in their
system including data centers and
they've looked into the future and they
can project that all what they believe
all the future data centers will use
about 200 acre feet of additional water
annually then I wanted to look at um
water because we have power generation
that I think is going to be coming and
we do have one example of that before us
today where they're going to be what we
call behind the meter.
Uh this uh project that uh is ongoing in
South Cheyenne today will be uh composed
of three different kinds of generation.
One is a fuel cell. Um they use natural
gas and I'm not quite sure I call it
magic because I don't quite understand
how it works. They don't burn the fuel,
but the fuel goes through a filter type
of a device that creates electricity.
The only byproducts are CO2 and water
vapor. And the CO2 will be sequestered.
Um, and there's no water at all used in
the process of of creating that
electricity. The second part of that
will be simple gas turbines. Uh, natural
gas is burned and the high-pressure
expanding gas directly spins the turbine
blades turning the generator. No water
is used in that process either. And then
the third phase will be combined cycle
turbines which is basically a simple uh
cycle turbine. But then the second phase
of that is used the heat to boil water
that is in a closed loop system. That
boiling water turns a secondary turbine
uh creating additional electricity and
the water is recycled and used over and
over and over again. Um I don't know
what's left for us to study when it
comes to water. Um we have a pretty good
handle on historic usage and I think our
board of public utilities has shared
with us they have studied and they have
a pretty good idea of what the future
looks like uh with the new technologies
and again when it comes to the health
and safety um welfare um
appreciate this is definitely an
important issue uh but again I'm not
sure exactly which staff would be
qualified to uh to do those
environmental health concerns. So Madam
Chairman um this ordinance asks us to
study five things. I think two of them
we have a pretty good handle on and the
other three I'm not sure our staff is
qualified to make those determinations.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. I just realized
Jennifer, did I have you read this item
in? Oh gosh. Okay, y'all are making me
nervous out there. Okay. Um, Councilman
Moody as sponsor, would you like to make
some comments?
>> Yes. Uh, thank you, Madam Chair. Just
wanted to mention I was told 30 minutes
before a meeting not to give a staff
report, but I'm still going to explain
the ordinance here, but thank you, Madam
Chairman. Uh Mark Moody, Shy City
Council Ward 3. Uh what you have in
front of you is an ordinance to impose a
temporary 12-month moratorum related
data centers. Before I go into details,
this was constituent driven. There are
petitions circulating asking the council
to adopt this. I think this came about
because of proposed Cox Ranch
annexation. This is a bipartisan issue.
I know the council is officially
nonpartisan and there have not been
foreign adversaries involved in this. I
think that is a distraction from the
main issue at hand. Uh the people
involved circling petitions are just
concerned citizens taking part in what
our constitutional republic uh involves.
And also for the record and I said this
on my interview with the news station
and also in my oped I'm not against data
centers has stayed numerous times. I
understand we need some for national
security and the ones here in town do
play a role in our economy. Okay. But
there's questions about the long-term
impacts and how many can we sustain.
Okay. That's what that's what I was
looking into. So I'll go proposed
ordinance and for the public I will also
mention the pages. I'm on page one right
now. Um I'll explain it by page and
section is so that way you can follow
along and also for the public has then
questions later on. Section one simply
states why we need this. Uh letter A
under section one emphasizes we're
responsible for the health, safety, and
welfare of our constituents. Letter B
and C going to uh current zoning
development codes do not address
uniqueness of data centers along with
how there's major public concern
regarding them. Letter D explains what
the moratorum does broadly. It goes more
detail in section two. And then letter D
explains the 12-month period will allow
city sap to study impacts and give us a
report regarding this. Again, we can
always, you know, find and find outside
help. We need it. We've done it for
traffic studies. We can even do it for
this. Section two gives details what the
moratorum entails. Okay, it's at the
bottom there of the page under E. I'll
read it verbatim. The governing body
hereby imposes a 12-month moratorum on
the processing, consideration, approval,
or issuance of any licenses, permits,
approvals, permitted uses, special uses,
accessory uses, site plans, conditional
uses, resoning, or variances that enable
or authorize the establishment,
construction, conversion of any building
or structure day center use with the
city. For the last part, for a public to
understand, wouldn't happen. If the
Hines building wanted to become a data
center, okay, wouldn't happen during the
12 months. They couldn't do it. And then
simply section three explains what the
moratorum does not do. As the first
sense states, this moratorum shall
again shall not apply data centers
currently under construction or repair
or replacement of existing data centers.
like adding more servers for instance
but shall apply data centers where
on-site construction has not commenced.
I know the question will come up
pertaining what is on-site construction
as day in the ordinance for the first
section on on-site construction means
the commencement of substantial physical
site work such as grading excavation or
foundation installation. It does not
include pre-construction activities such
as design, engineering, permitting,
financing, equipment procurement or
contractual commitments. So essentially
if dirt is moved, if dirt is moved, then
it is under construction. Okay. As soon
as the shovel's on the ground and then
section three onwards towards the bottom
there and it goes on to page two. Okay.
The last sentence states any
applications pertaining to data centers
that have not begun on-site construction
shall be held in advance during
dependency moratorum until mortorium is
expired. Pretty much what it means is
applications are temporarily paused.
Okay. When the moratorium's in effect
unless the applicant elects to withdraw
their application any required timelines
to an application shall be told for the
duration of the moratorum. City staff
shall provide notice to any applicants
of the moratorium and tolling period
means city staff has to inform the
applicants this moratorum begins on this
date ends on that date and any fees paid
the city shall be refunded to any
applicant who likes to withdraw
application to the establishment
construction or conversion of a building
structure to the data center that is
delayed as a result of this moratorum.
So essentially the city will refund your
Monday and if the question comes up of
what it would look like I've not
inquired about you know how much money
that we'd have to refund I can get that
for our Tuesday meeting. So I just want
everybody know I will ask that question.
I know a question is going to come up. I
can ask that and we'll have that
information in for the money meeting.
And then on page two, it just simply
says uh explains the city staff from
various departments need to study the
impacts on data centers on the
environment, electricity rates, power
grid, water usage, any other factors
related to health, safety, welfare of
the city's residents. I know what's come
up. I would say, you know, let's get
some apartments involved. Planning
department, engineering, board of public
utilities. We have to get outside for
other impacts. You know, I'm pretty sure
people in the public would definitely
support that. And I would say study the
closed loop system in more detail. I
know leadeds in the board of public
utilities has provided us uh this sheet
right here saying how much water usage
there is. I agree it is 1.2%.
But we have to look at the long-term
impacts. Okay, the long-term aspects and
also what was not mentioned impacts
agriculture outside the city impacts
potential land value impacts to
groundwater. Okay, so it's not
exhaustive. There could be other factors
that come up. And then it says staff
shall report the results of the study
governing body no later than April 1st,
2027. Shall include recommendations
going by for any changes to applicable
codes, rules, or regulations. So would
be required to be due by April 1st for
use in to give us recommendations for
codes, zoning, public notice
requirements. Again, it's not
exhaustive.
And then just section five justly says
where data center term comes in with the
UDC code. Okay, it's 1.4.4F.
Again, if the public wants to reference
this and we know section six and senator
standard, but I have additional things
why sponsors too. We know recently there
was an outcry in Utah regarding this.
This is a bipartisan issue. Going to
keep emphasizing it that's occurring
throughout the whole country. Okay, I'll
not read off an exhaustive list.
temporary moratoriums that have come
about. But recently, Hill County, Texas,
implemented one literally just a week
ago. Politically, it's like Cheyenne,
Larry County. One county opposite of us,
Champagne County, Illinois, just
recently uh implemented one. Finley,
Ohio just did one, too. Tulso, Oklahoma.
Indianapolis, Indiana's in the beginning
stages of it. Oklahoma City, again,
theirs is a little bit different.
They're looking more at the wage aspect.
Okay. But again, that's where I got all
this information from. It's from other
municipalities across the country and
constituents do have questions related
to more water usees electricity. I know
that modern data center, I said before,
use the closed loop system. Okay, I
understand that. But again, we have to
look at long-term impacts and we have 12
to 13 in operation. So 1.2 right now
does not see much. I understand that.
But if there's proposals for 40 to 70, I
can't verify 70, but I can verify 40 to
43. That's been mentioned numerous from
numerous sources, that's definitely
going to have some impact on border
usage, even if it is open air. Okay.
What about during say the summer months
and I know Black Hills Energy does have
tariff uh with up to lows of 13 watts.
However, this is short-term technology
is constantly changing. could
potentially require more power usage.
Substations data centers have could be
maxed out require tapped into the main
uh grid. Another thing to keep in mind
is Wyman statue and I do have it here
and again if the public wants to write
this down 37-3-116
and this is from the first sentence an
electric utility may
may enter into service green as
specified in subsection D and that's
again all the agreements there. So,
they're not required to do it. Other
utility companies, not, you know, let's
say, I'm not saying now, but 30 years
down the road, Black Hill says, "We're
not doing it anymore." Okay? We're all,
you know, long gone and not here.
They could they they could uh cancel it.
Words have meaning. Okay? Words do have
meaning. Where Governor DeSantis of
Florida just signed a law saying that
all power companies shall enter these
agreements throughout the state of
Florida that want to have data.
Councilman Moody, please stay on the
topic of this moratorium amenia in Larmy
County.
>> Okay. I will just uh explain right here
where it has to deal with with regards
to the uh another reason why I'd also
say let's look at the uh land usage of
225 acres and the um also in terms of
impacts with the agriculture. But I will
end with this security considerations
need to be considered. That's not been
talked about at all. Lowden County,
Virginia does have 200 data centers, but
it proximity to Washington DC and major
federal facilities provides love
deterrence that Cheyenne does not have
despite the air force base there. Okay,
Wyoming is one of the most rural states.
A dense cluster of data centers just
here in Cheyenne, not spread out. Again,
not spread out. Okay, that could be a
target for adversaries. Okay, yes, we
have the missile sites. Yes, we have the
Air Force security forces that guard
them. Okay. But again, they're not going
to focus on data centers. Okay. We have
to also keep that in mind. Okay. It's
not good to build them cluster them
together. Again, the ones in Virginia,
they've been there since the '9s. And
again, data centers were a lot smaller
back then, too. We also have to take
that in consideration when they were
playing this out 20 years ago. They were
smaller. They weren't these big ones.
So, that's all I have. Hope I also went
into some questions that could have been
asked. And again, I'll stand for any
more questions you may have. Hope I
answered all of them.
>> Thank you. Uh, Councilman Moody.
Okay. So, like I said, we're gonna
people can come up to both sides. I want
this to be respectful. Please, let's not
make it personal or anything like that.
And um remember the three minute clock.
Is there anything else?
>> Okay. and and give us your name and your
ward, please.
>> My name is Christina Heckton. I'm not
sure of my ward. I live in Indian Hills.
Um, I've got a full thing on the record
today for public record, but I'm going
to give you a short thing. I'm here
today to represent the most vulnerable
person in our community, the disabled,
the senior citizens, and those who have
intellectual and cognitive disabilities
or medical conditions that have found
our doctors telling us that we should no
longer be working because it'll kill us,
literally. We did not ask to be this
way, but to no fault to our own, here we
are. Severe medical disabilities of all
kinds, and we are told by everyone that
if we cannot make it in today's economy,
it is our own choice. If we have actual
medical papers from doctors, there
should be employers that are willing and
able to accommodate us during these
times. The one place in town that helps
us pays only 850 an hour and we can work
4 hours two times a day. And the DVR no
longer has employers reach out to them
to help us because in my opinion, we're
too much work. We take too long to
learn. We're not strong enough. We don't
have a college degree. And our life
experiences through trial and hardship
do not count. Those like me have come
from all over Wyoming to live here in
Cheyenne because in 2014, it was the
only place to receive long-term help
with DD waivers and traumatic brain
injury waivers. Cheyenne has the staff
and companies that are expected
practically to be CNAs in some instances
for 13 to $15 an hour. The city council
for public record is getting a $1,000
cost of living raise at election time
because you can't make it in this
economy. Me and others like me are
living off of $1,000 a month per no
choice. My question is in 10 years from
now if I'm no longer here to advocate
for my daughter who's also severely
disabled or myself is as follows. Is a
tap water going to still turn on when I
turn on my faucet? Are a gas and
electricity for a thousand square foot
household going to go over the 300
amount? And can you get it in writing?
because the $100 delivery fee and the on
gas and the separate $100 on electric
delivery fee is killing us every month.
It was only 98 when we moved here in
2014.
Or do we need your permanent long-term
residents that moved here because every
place else in Wyoming is a medical
desert? Do we need to start looking for
other places to live in Exodus and seek
of water, food, shelter, and medicine?
We need accessible information with
actual facts about what's happening for
those who are not good at researching or
technology like myself. I've made do
without technology before, but I cannot
make do without the basic necessities.
That's all I have to say today.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Thank you, Mr. White.
Uh
>> through you, Madam Chairman, Michael
White, Larie County. Um,
this is kind of tough for me to say, but
I respect the rules that are given to us
today. But I find it interesting
that when when we mention data centers,
the public is allowed to speak for three
minutes.
Other people can speak as long as they
want. So I going to question a point of
order today on that. I support Mr.
Moody's ordinance.
Every meeting that I've been to that we
should be able to talk about Dana
Centers, we were told
that nobody knew about this
planning commission didn't know.
Public comment on the council did not
know about data centers.
We continue
to hear information.
We were told by the developer that in
one to two weeks after the the first the
second meeting that we would have public
comment with them. That has not
happened. I urge everybody in this room
and with respect to this governing body
that listen to what the people in the
back here are saying.
We need information and the time frame
that we have to address is not enough.
We need this moratorum. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Mr. White.
>> Jim Chur for W one candidate. See a lot
of passion here. I see a lot of folks on
both sides either for or against us
here. I just want to kind of take a a
survey here. the ones that you find
union workers that we have here, the
electricians, carpenters, that how many
of you live in Cheyenne by a show of
hand. Okay,
so that's a good thing. But think of the
impact that this is going to go and
make. Okay, news flash for you. Elon
Musk is planning on putting data centers
up in space. Won't need that cooling.
Then what do we do with all these extra
buildings that we have out there? I
don't want to take away from your
families, from your your food in your
your mouths and that, but there's other
options that I have if I get on to
cityial council baseball stadium uh you
know a uh get rid of the mall and get an
outlet mall. There's plenty other things
that we can go and do that.
>> Mr. Ser, please stay on the moratorum.
>> Right. And this this I I highly
encourage this moratorum is what we need
to go and have on there. It needs to be
a study. There needs to not just I hate
I beg to differ with the with the
mayor's uh impact with the water and
that relatives of mine live up there in
Phoenix. Okay, they just went and uh
turned down the uh data center for
Chandler and that and the the impact
with the water is just like your car.
They have to flush out the radio. They
have to flush that out. I don't want
Cheyenne to turn into another love canal
for those of you old enough to remember
that. And it's got to go somewhere.
We're not going to go and put it into
our our waste treatment center. It's
going to have to go somewhere. So, I
highly encourage you guys to do this
moratorum.
>> Thank you,
>> Madam Chairman.
>> Mr. Leborn.
>> Thank you. I just want to remind
everyone to speak into the microphone.
It's really important both for those of
us that don't hear as well as they used
to as well as the people online.
And it is uh certainly something that is
easy to look around, turn your head, uh
don't lower the microphone and have it
near your mouth. That happens. But I'm
sure everyone here wants to be able to
hear and we want the people that are
listening online to do that as well. So
I would really urge the public, Madam
Chairman, to be careful about speaking
into the microphone. Thank you.
>> Thank Whoops. Go ahead, Heather. Good
afternoon, Heather Madrid. Um, I am here
in support of the moratorium ordinance.
I sent the council an email last night
detailing the ways in which a moratorium
is legal and warranted. I included
credible sources to interpret land land
use regulations in Wyoming. I pointed to
article 13 section one of the Wyoming
constitution which gives the largest
measure of self-government government to
cities and towns. I shared Wyoming
statute 9-8-301
which requires cities to develop a
comprehensive land use plan. Plan
Cheyenne hasn't been updated in 12
years. It should have been updated twice
since then. I expressed concerns with
the changes to the UDC in 2022 that
changed the definition for data centers
from heavy industrial to light
industrial allowing them to build in the
everexpanding business parks without the
need for public input.
At that time, we were told that this was
a routine update and later changes would
involve public input. Later never came
and that small change in 2022 blew the
doors wide open for what is now a
free-for-all. The response I got from
Mr. Esabel was that approving the
moratorium would lead to property rights
lawsuits and loss of jobs for hundreds
of workers. Both valid points. However,
current projects with vested rights can
be grandfathered in, protecting the
rights of developers and the jobs of
people currently working on
construction. This is was successfully
done in Laden County, Virginia, which
has the highest concentration of data
centers in the country. This temporary
moratorum is legally justified due to
the major planning gaps and the need for
cumulative impact studies. The troubling
part of Mr. Exel's condescending
response was the accusation that the
valid concerns of Cheyenne residents is
driven by propaganda from foreign
actors. The support for data centers is
very well funded at corporate
billionaires, energy firms, and local
economic development groups like
Cheyenne Leads. The union has is well
represented here. I have to wonder if
they're paid to be here. I can tell you
that I am not.
Um there is traceable evidence of those
funding streams. Whereas the so-called
evidence for the dark money theory was
funded by the American Energy Institute
and claimed 39 million in foreign
funding. 39 million. Project Jade alone
will cost $50 billion
to build according to project
representatives. So you tell me which
side of this issue is better funded
according to solid evidence. Mr. ESel
claimed do due diligence and referenced
the more than qualified engineers and
hydraologists employed by the city. What
about independent environmental
scientists, zoning attorneys,
telecommunications architects, cyber
security and physical security
specialists, acoustical engineers, air
quality experts, fiscal impact analysts,
labor market economists, public health
experts, psychological and neurological
health experts, just to name a few.
Lastly, I would like to point you to
article 1, section one of the Wyoming
Constitution, which states that all
power is inherent in the people and
governments are founded on their
authority and instituted for their
peace, safety, and happiness. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Miss Madrid.
>> My name is Ryan Ao. I'm of Ward One. I'm
a local resident and member of Lyuna
Laborers Local 1271. And I'm not paid to
be here. Before my union job on the meta
project Cosmo data center, I was making
$13 an hour and 32 hours a week in the
hotel industry. Here at Fortis, I was
earning $28 an hour at 40 hours a week
with medical, dental, retirement, and
education benefits. This is a
life-changing difference. Because of
that life-changing difference, I was
recently able to purchase a mobile home,
giving me a level of stability and a
quality of life here that simply wasn't
available before. I am a local resident
investing in my future right here in
Cheyenne. The concern about out ofstate
workers that I've heard is that are
taking these jobs is legitimate and I
hear it. A moratorium doesn't fix that
problem. It eliminates the jobs
entirely. One area worth focusing on is
ensuring that these companies are held
to local hiring, prioritizing union
labor for every trade role that we can
fill and chey residents for all other
eligible positions before workers come
in from out of state. Data centers also
grow the whole economy. More workers
means more people in hotels,
restaurants, and shops. I worked in
hospitality. I've seen both sides. I
hold an a degree in environmental
policy. Um I worked as an eir
environmental impact report consultant
for a while. Wyoming's cooler climate
and wind already make our data centers
among the least water intensive in the
nation.
And to the space data point, Elon Musk
has admitted that those will not become
a complete solution because of the lag
time. So we will still need terrestrial
based data centers always. Um,
remarkably AI is solving its own
environmental footprint, engineering
better heat management for its own
chips, more efficient solar materials to
power itself, and cleaner algorithms
that do more with less energy. Pausing
new data centers doesn't stop
consumption. It locks us into older,
dirtier technology while innovation
moves on without us. Environmental
impact reports happen before the
approval process and there is a public
comment time allowed. Mitigations and
alternatives are part of the
environmental impact process. A friend
said it simply, we have to manage this
technology, not fight it. A moratorium
isn't management, it's retreat. Wyoming
has a window to lead. Let's not hand it
to someone else. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
Miss McCoy.
>> Thank you, Councilwoman Emmens. My name
is Patricia McCoy and I'm a resident of
Laramie County. I'm standing here today
alongside many of my neighbors because
we are demanding transparency,
accountability, and a seat at our own
table. For months, the citizens of
Cheyenne have been subjected to a slow
drip of information. We watch as massive
tracks of land like the 12,200 acre Cox
Ranch property being quietly annexed or
reszoned under generic light industrial
labors. Only after the ink is
practically dry do we discover that
these deals were cut behind closed doors
using non-disclosure agreements. What is
most alarming is that it isn't just the
citizens being shut out. We have all
watched recent council meetings where it
became embarrassingly clear that even
our own city council members are being
kept completely out of the loop. When
the very representatives we elected to
vet these projects are left scratching
their heads, asking basic questions
about resource consumption and finding
out details at the exact same time as
the general public. The system is
fundamentally broken. NDAs have no place
in local government. When administration
officials sign NDAs with multi-billion
dollar tech corporations, you aren't
just blinding the public, you're
blinding our legislative body. You're
choosing to represent a corporate bottom
line over the citizens who put you in
office. Organizations like Cheyenne
Leads are actively circulating flyers
attempting to dismiss our very real
data-driven concerns as misinformation
or being from foreign governments. Lived
here 18 years, ain't nobody paying me.
They claim we are uneducated on this
issue. So let's look at the actual data.
You want to talk scale. We're not
talking one to two data centers or
facilities. We have recently learned
that there are as many as 40 43 or even
70 data center projects at various
stages of discussion in our area. The
resource drain, they tell you it's a
closed loop system. It's modern. It's
not going to use that much water. Well,
you're going to use a ton when you fill
it. You're going to use a ton every time
you flush it and refill it. And where
does that water go? H into our lands
exactly where they shouldn't be. These
hypers scale developments create an
initial construction boom using yes
outofstate labor with our labor. But
once operational, they provide very few
permanent local jobs. Meanwhile, our
community is left vulnerable to the same
boom and bust cycles that have
historically hurt Wyoming. We are not
misinformed. We are paying attention and
clearly we are doing more homework than
the people cutting these deals. We are
here today to strongly support the
12-month moratorum on new data center
approvals. A pause is a responsible
protective measure. It gives our city
staff and you, our council members, the
necessary time to study the cumulative
impacts on our utility rates,
groundwater, and infrastructure before
our resources are completely spoken for.
We need clear, heavyweed regulations and
strict guidelines, not corporate
exemptions. Remember who you work for.
McCoy, your time is up. Thank you. Of
>> course it is.
>> Hi Hannah Jackson from W 3. I'm in
support of the moratorum for reasons
that have already been stated. And while
I understand the union is saying that a
lot of the jobs are coming from there
and yes, some will have to come out.
doesn't we don't have every
technological export expert in Cheyenne
and I don't want them to lose their
jobs. I don't believe they would but a
pause to give us time to gather
information and make sure that we are
all educated as a community to safeguard
our community, our children's future and
their community's future is what we
should do. There are plenty of things
that are going on in other states that
have shown us that maybe it's not as
clear-cut as we see. We see this with
everything. So, let's take a pause, like
she said earlier. Let's find the
information we need. Let's give
transparency to our community because
that's what we're asking for. People
will be more calm if we understand. And
if there are NDAs, I'm sure that they
can explain things without jeopardizing
whether it's
intellectual
things that they want to keep to themsel
because it affects their business
process. That doesn't mean they can't
explain things enough to give us an
understanding of what's going on and
what will go on in our community and how
it may affect us. The long term is what
we're all concerned about here, not just
the short term. And I highly hope that
you guys will take this mortorium so
that we can get the information and
everybody I talk we as the whole as the
governing body and as the people. So I
please thank you for considering.
>> Thank you. Just for the record there are
no city councilmen that have signed an
NDA on anything. So I don't know exactly
where that's coming from. Uh, just so
you know, nobody up here has signed an
NDA.
Go ahead,
>> Kathy Sigiano. W three. Um, first I do
want to say that I do appreciate the
skilled workers that are here. I
encourage you to participate in anything
that has to do with our community,
whether you have lived here or you have
just come here. I have just a few
questions. I want to know the top five
benefits that I will receive from data
centers as a member of this community
because the mayor mentioned at a meeting
last week how beneficial these will be
for our community. So I would just like
five top things that I will benefit on
these. I would like to know if I can get
assurances that my electricity bill and
my water bill will not increase over the
next 10 years. Is there any kind of
mechanism that is going to be installed
on any of these lines that will ensure
that data centers can't use more water
than they are asking for? I would like
to know if our infrastructure as it
currently sits now can handle the
proposed 70 data centers. Obviously,
we've been told maybe that's not quite
going to be 70. So, I appreciate that
information. Along with the 5,600
workers that are possibly going to be
coming here, and if not, what
improvements will be done in order to
support those needs, are we getting more
law enforcement in the city and in the
county? Will you be talking to local
businesses about hiring issues since we
will be increasing in population
significantly? Are you talking to our
local high schools and colleges in the
state about programs that can be offered
to our kids so that they can go into
these jobs versus hiring out of state?
And I don't mean lower paying jobs. I
mean the actual good jobs that we keep
being told that are like six figures.
Um let's see. I would like to um ask you
to consider these questions along with
so many questions that people have asked
over the several months that we have
been discussing these at city council
meetings. Again, I am not against the
workforce that's coming here. I'm not
against growth. I just want it done
smart and balanced so that our community
does benefit from this. Just a little
bit of information. My family came here
12 years ago from North Dakota. My
husband had an oil field job. I know
exactly what a boom looks like for a
community. We were called oil field
trash because we moved to a small town
that only had 500 people and that grew
significantly. I don't want to be
someone treating the workers that are
coming here like this. I won't be that
person. Um I just want our city to
understand the benefits, be transparent,
and just open and communicate with us.
Thank you.
>> Thank you,
>> Madam Chair, committee. My name is Marcy
Kindred. I'm the executive director of
the Wyoming State AFL CIO. I'm here with
some of the hardest working people in
Laramie County. Electricians, pipe
fitters, carpenters, operators, the ones
who are building these facilities and
the young apprentices who are just
starting their careers and will learn
the craft building these projects. I
understand why people are concerned. AI
and data centers have taken over a lot
of the public discourse nationally.
There are plenty of horror stories
filling our feeds about data centers
devastating communities. I am proud and
grateful that my community is engaged on
this issue, demanding transparency and
making sure Cheyenne does not become the
next cautionary tale. But the great news
is Wyoming is good at this. We have
extensive processes and safeguards in
place. It may feel like these proposals
have dropped out of the sky, but we have
been building data centers in Cheyenne
for over a decade. The answer to a lot
of these concerns exists. water usage,
rateayer protections, environmental
impacts, they're publicly available.
They always have been. And I want to
acknowledge the government employees who
put that work in. Um, and acknowledge
the frustration that must be felt by
city council members and these employees
being accused of lack of transparency
when so much work has been done. These
processes are complicated, however, and
I struggle to keep up with the meetings
and the proposals myself, and that's
part of my job. But the community is
here now engaged and asking for more,
and the state fed is here to be part of
that solution. We're ready to help
facilitate that conversation. Town
halls, pages on websites, whatever we
need. But we are strongly opposed to
hitting the pause button as an answer.
Our opposition to this moratorum is not
a broad endorsement of AI. Thank you
chairwoman for keeping us on topic at uh
today. But I do want to acknowledge that
what I believe is the source of a lot of
the heartburn because I think we all
have serious concerns about lack of
federal regulation and the very real
threat this poses to America's
workforce. But none of us in this room
have much say over any of that. These
data centers will be built. If not here,
then somewhere with a rubber stamp ready
and far fewer safeguards. The fight over
AI belongs in Washington. Today's
question is simpler. Should we risk the
possibility of losing these
opportunities for our local workforce?
Our answer is no. Because here's what a
moratorum actually means for our
workers. It means sending them down the
road. It means weekends driving home
from Colorado or Utah, missing a kid's
ball game, missing a recital, sleeping
in a hotel instead of their own bed. For
decades, Wyoming's skilled trades have
been traveling halls. Our people have
had to leave home to find work.
>> These projects changed all of that.
>> For the first time in a long time,
they're here.
>> Thank you.
>> Hey.
Hello, my name is Gregory Barrow. I'm in
Ward 3, I believe, and I just wanted to
say a few words about these uh data
centers. Uh, as you know, there's been a
a big collection of signatures against
it. I'm in support of this moratorum. I
believe the homework hasn't been done
especially in Cheyenne here as far as
the environment goes as fel as far as
the water usage and
how much can we trust because there's
been a data center down in outside of
Atlanta, Georgia and apparently the
water lines there was two different
connections that weren't monitored and
they used to the tune of 30 million
gallons of water and it was discovered
when the residents were the ones turning
the water on, they had low water
pressure and that's how they ended up
finding out about that. So, um, besides
that, I I do want to say to the trades,
you know, I'm all for the trades and
working. I I spent my life in the
trades, so I have nothing against that.
I don't want to see anybody lose their
job, but I think we need a moratorum on
this until we have some more studies.
And as the uh mayor said, there may not
be people on the staff that are actually
qualified to do some of these studies.
So, something else I read about these
data centers was um I forget exactly
where it was, but there they were doing
studies on the temperature of the ground
and they went five miles away from where
the data center was and it had raised
the temperature 10 to 15 degrees, 5 to
six miles away. So, what's that going to
do to our land here? You know, those
kind of studies need to happen before we
approve this. who's going to pay for
these high power lines that was just
brought to my attention earlier, you
know, that are going to be needed. Um,
so my basic question is why why do we
need these data centers? I don't believe
that the internet is that slow or that
we need to be on top of we got enough
data centers. We don't need more of
them. I mean, it's surveillance. That's
another name for this is besides AI,
it's surveillance. You got all these
flock cameras now around our city,
right? So you can watch us and monitor
us. And this is another form of
surveillance. It's going to turn into
we're paying
as residents here. We're paying for this
stuff to happen or the billionaires are
paying. We're going to end up paying
later. uh to where they're going to
monitor us more now and be able to uh
get into social media feeds and all that
and it seems like a takeover of the
state. Okay? And I don't like to see
that stuff happen. I I can I grew up
without a cell phone, without the
internet, and I could do it again,
believe me. And we all can. We don't
need this heavy dependence on it. Thank
you,
>> Mr. Bear.
>> Thank you.
Oh,
if one side can't do it, the other side
can't do it. So, let's just not do it.
So,
>> yeah, my name's Bill Strickland. I'm
with Ward One. Um, you know, yes, last
night I was just sitting there and I
kind of did a little bit of homework
and, uh, you know, in the last five
years, we've used less water than we did
five years ago by quite a bit. And
actually over the last 30 years, BOPU
has seen a decrease in the water usage
in Laram County. I I would I would guess
we have some pretty good figures as to
what these things are going to use
already. I am against this moratorum. I
think we ought to build more.
Um, you know, as far as electricity,
these guys already know that there's
going to be a large load tariff on the
electricity if they have to get more
electricity in them. A lot of them are
building their own power plants like
they talked about earlier.
Um,
but I think the biggest real benefit is
the amount of property taxes we get. In
2025,
13 AI companies paid 14 million in
property taxes. That can go a long ways,
a really long ways in education, in
development, road construction,
um just all kinds of things. And you
know, my last point I guess I'd like to
make is I was listening to Channel 5
News. Don't ask me why, but I was. Um,
and they were they were talking about
the hospital.
They can't keep doctors. They can't pay
them enough.
Maybe some of these property taxes and
stuff can help us get more doctors here
to keep the doctors that we have. That's
going to help immensely.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Thank you, madam. Madam Chairman,
>> I'm Donna Wolf, W three, and I support
this moratorum. The sheer volume of the
proposed 43 to 70 centers represents
massive industrial growth in a very
short time and the amount of information
about the whole process and the effects
on the community is hard to find,
understand or verify. I want I I want a
moratorum to give us time to address a
few points. Everyone's talking about how
these newer centers are more efficient,
draw less energy, won't uh impact the
water supply, but what about the noise
pollution? from their constant buzzing
like a lawn mower running 24/7. Not to
mention the air pollution caused by
these their emissions. In a region prone
to wildfires, we don't need anything
more to worsen our air quality. I know
these these will bring in a lot of money
to the state, county, city, but where
will it go? And will we have any say in
how it's spent? I would particularly
like to see funds for increasing our
police to be able to enforce existing
speeding laws and noise ordinances.
Cheyenne has become an incredibly noisy
traffic hub, and I can't imagine it
getting any better with a revolving
workforce of 5600 workers, even when
they have their own housing. We need to
get our own house in order before we
welcome visitors such as these temporary
workers, no matter how however long
temporary is. Yesterday, I learned that
data centers moving to Wyoming do not
require an industrial sighting permit
originally enacted to minimize the
impact of massive industry on local
communities. Data centers have been
allowed to sidestep this just by being
located in a county designated
industrial or business park. I can I
call this an escape an escape clause,
but this at least explains the city and
county involvement. There is not enough
unbiased, independently sourced
information for us to make an informed
decision. I want to believe that we have
a voice in this grand scheme. We live
here. We deserve to know what's coming
for us and how Cheyenne and the county
are prepared to deal with it all. To
protect our quality of life, I urge the
city council and county commissioners to
use the moratorum to re-examine the
industrial sighting act and other
permitting processes to remove any ex
escape clauses to better balance the
needs of the community versus the
explosive industrial growth from as many
as 70 data centers. Thank you.
Go ahead.
>> Hi, my name is Chloe Edmonds. I'm with
W.
>> Get it real close to you
>> like that.
>> There you go.
>> Hi, my name is Chloe Edmonds. I'm with
Ward 3. Um, I work through the labors
local 1271 and I am also not paid to be
here today. I chose to come um as a
single mom of two kids. I've had a lot
of struggles in the job world causing a
lot of financial stress for my family
until I joined the local and got placed
in one of the data centers being
constructed here in town. These
opportunities have afforded a better
lifestyle for me and my kids. It makes
it easier to have the work in town when
I can't travel with my children due to
their education. I'm in front of you
today to bring the awareness to the
damage the moratorum would do to people
in my shoes with whom I have a lot of
working experience especially after all
of the budget cuts with the food stamps
and the Medicaid and now my kids were
really struggling with me. Having got
this job, I now have insurance and a
retirement fund and that has made a lot
of difference. So in conclusion,
>> please don't go forward with the
moratorum. Thank you.
>> Thank you,
>> Madam Chair, uh, committee. I'm Michael
Larson, War 3, and um,
I do support this moratorum. I went
online this morning to read the Cowboy
State Daily and I saw at the top of the
page understanding Microsoft's community
first approach and I thought to myself
this is too good to be true. It really I
didn't believe it. I don't believe it
because when I started looking into I'm
not wasn't that familiar with any of
this. I started looking into how these
data centers got permitted got uh
approved. There used to be uh a process
the industrial site act which would um
look into these applications and say
well this is a large industrial
project. We have to look at it with all
all our resources, all our expertise,
things that local governments and city
councils might not have access to, and
we're going to have to make a decision
if we can uh, you know, approve of their
permit or not. But that's not the case.
These guys are given these guys are
given a, you know, a go-ahad to go ahead
and, you know, a way around this. they
were able to avoid these kind of
reviews. It was left up to, you know,
small government, city council to
decide. This is a loophole. I think this
so-called exclusion that uh is is called
an exclusion. I don't think that's
right. I think the issue of a huge
number of data centers wanting to come
here, it's too big an issue to be
decided by just a few hands and the
decisions aren't too important to be
rushed just so that data centers can
come online as fast as they can. That's
not right. So that's why I support this
moratorum and I encourage all the
residents of Cheyenne and Laramie County
to demand transparent, transparency,
clarity, get more informed, more
involved. Thank you. Thank you, sir.
>> My name is Crystal Edmonds Carter. I'm a
resident of Cheyenne, a member of
Labor's Local 1271. I'm here today to
speak from the perspective of the
workers and the families whose
livelihoods are tied to the data
center's industry. For many people in
our community, these jobs are not just
numbers on a development report. They
are opportunities that have changed
lives. These projects are putting single
mothers and people that don't want to
travel to work. They are giving
opportunity to people who cannot travel
for work or leave homes for weeks at a
time. They are allowing parents to stay
close to their children and families
while still earning a strong living.
These are high-paying jobs with
insurance, health benefits, and
stability that many workers in Cheyenne
struggle to find elsewhere. For a lot of
families, these jobs mean being a able
to afford rent, groceries, child care,
and the rising utility bills. I
understand the concerns surrounding data
centers. As a resident, I also worry
about infrastructure, water usage,
energy demands, and the rising cost of
utilities. Those concerns are real and
they deserve serious attention. I
believe there absolutely should be
checks and balance system in place to
ensure these facilities are built
responsibly and operated the way
companies promise they will be. But I
also ask the council to consider the
workers and families who depend on these
opportunities. The a moratorum could
slow or stop jobs that are helping local
people build stable lives right here in
Cheyenne.
We put our trust in our elected
officials and governing bodies to create
strong relationships, enforce
accountability, and protect the
community. The answer should not be
stopping opportunity altogether. The
answer is smart oversight, responsible
growth, and clear standards that protect
residents while allowing people to keep
working. Please create these regulations
these companies need to follow, but also
protect the jobs that are helping
Cheyenne families succeed. Thank you for
your time.
>> Thank you.
K. McAdams, 67year resident of Cheyenne,
Wyoming.
Today, I was supposed to be at a
remembrance for a son who died serving
his country in Afghanistan in 2014.
Instead, this time is being spent here
because his daughter, my granddaughter
Maddie,
and future generations of Cheyenne
residents will have to live with
long-term consequences of the decisions
being made today.
A temporary moratorum simply gives us
time to think.
There are already data centers that are
going to be built. So, there's no job
loss right now that I can see. Somebody
can correct me with that. It gives us
time to fully analyze long-term impacts
and time to ensure growth is balanced
with protection of Cheyenne's water
infrastructure, taxpayers, and future
generations.
That is why a temporary moratorium on a
largecale data center development is
being requested. A mortorium would
provide Cheyenne with more time, more
transparency and more independent
analysis before moving forward. One
major concern is water lands aquifer.
Once groundwater is removed, it cannot
simply be assumed that those resources
can sustain unlimited long-term demand
infinitely
indefinitely. Recently, residents were
told that one project and you can fix me
if I'm wrong because the information
comes so fast that you have to have time
to think about it. Hence the moratorum.
So one acre foot equals about 325
gallons of water. 200 acre feet roughly
65 million gallons of water per year or
approximately 178 gallons per day.
Enough to supply about 350 average
Wyoming households for an entire year.
So I do not know that figure. That
figure means nothing to me. So I need to
know how many data centers are coming
and that sort of thing. That's why the
mortorium the moratoriums need it.
Residents deserve independent scientific
analysis from Wyoming public water
officials and hydraologists, not only
from industry representatives. For
example, I was at the water board thing.
Steve Delanco of Net Choice Organization
represents a technology industry trade
association. He is not a neutral
hydraologist or a public utility expert.
He is being paid $400,000 a year for
this. Before decisions of this scale are
made, the public deserves independent
Wyoming board analysis.
There are other concerns. I'm not even
going to get into them. I'll be the next
meeting, I'm sure. Um, I'll bring up
past planning mistakes that Cheyenne
made in my residency that cost the city
$300,000 because they ramroded Thomas
Heights through. Do not ramrod these
data centers. You have an opportunity
now to have a moratorum so that you can
think, please. I support the moratorum.
>> Thank you, Miss McAdams.
No,
don't do that,
sir.
>> Council members, Charles Hendricks, Ward
One. I'm a resident. Um, I'm here with a
lot of my colleagues. We are not paid to
be here. We are here by choice. I am
opposed to the moratorum.
A moratorium is not the answer. Um, 12
months is an eternity in data center
world. 12 months is
it's going to stop people from building.
It's going to stop them from coming.
It's going to stop them from looking. My
opinion,
there's a lot of places that are doing
moratoriums right now as was already
stated by the by the man that was up
here. Um,
it's not Cheyenne. It's not Wyoming.
And from the amount that I've heard at
this event and many others, there's a
lot of mis misinformation out there on
data centers. I'm not going to go into
any of that. I think from the mayor's
report said it best. I don't need to
delve into any of that stuff. I would
support a public information campaign to
get rid of some of that disinformation
over a moratorum.
Wyoming as a natural resource exporter
is top five or six per capita. they rise
to the top of that list.
Data is a resource that is needed
everywhere and I think Wyoming Cheyenne
has an amazing opportunity here to be at
the front of that when so many other
places are saying no and putting 12
months on corporations that are not
going to wait 12 months. They're going
to go somewhere else. So, as a union
carpenter,
as an employer, I'm a superintendent. I
have half my crew here today that are
all residents of this area. I'd love to
see this moratorum just stopped right
here, right now. That's all I got.
Thanks.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Hi, Andma.
I am in support of this moratorum
because my background is in technology.
I love technology when it's used
correctly.
Over the years, I honestly don't see how
it has truly benefited humanity.
This technology, data centers, they're
resource hungry. I'm sure we could do
better, but right now this is what we're
given.
And then I wonder what is actually being
done in these data centers. What kind of
data is being collected, stored? Why do
we need to do all of this? There's so
much more surveillance technology. You
look at the Ring doorbells, monitor
this, monitor that, collect the
biometric data. I just heard recently
that Ford Motors is going to be
installing a sensor in their vehicles
that will scan your biometrics and
determine if you if it is safe for you
to drive and will not allow you to turn
the your truck on. I do not know if
that's true or not, but things like that
I think is overstepping our sovereignty
as humanity. It is getting into control
way. It's way too much. Um
I think it's all about controlling
money. And when
I see the former CEO of Microsoft is on
record for stating that we need to
control the population,
that raises an alarm bell. And more
recently when he was stated or when he
stated that we need to block the sun
to prevent global warming that's a
little
offkilter there. um
data center the
manufacturing
is important but why can't we do
something that we actually make
something because this manufacturing
this building is temporary it will go on
for x amount of time and then it's done
and then what is being produced after
that it collects data
our data I don't want my data being
collected
If we could switch it to actually be to
actually produce something that is a
benefit to all and not just to some, I
think that's the way to go. Thank you.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Mr. Fagan,
>> Madam Chair, Tucker Fagan. I'm W one. Uh
I'm in against the moratorum. Here's
why. I was one of eight people that uh
built in the US strategic war plan. And
then I was ahead of the uh joint chiefs
of staff uh nuclear warfare section. AI
is probably the most strongest weapon
you will ever find. Stronger than a
carrier battle group, stronger than an
intercontinental ballistic missile. The
Chinese command-driven economy, they're
way ahead of us. You look last week, the
head of open AI said we are woefully
deficient in the infrastructure for AI
in the United States.
Number two, in economic development, I
learned that you play the hand you've
been dealt. So, look at uh Sweetwater
County, they were dealt Trona. Look at
Campbell County. They were dealt uh coal
and and gas. What are we dealt? This
This is our next play. Look at Campbell
County in the 50s and 60s when the coal
companies came there. people looked at
them and said, "Hey, we've seen what
you've done in Pennsylvania and West
Virginia. You are not going to hurt our
oil, our air, our land, and and our
infrastructure." And look at them today
because we set the guidelines. The
people in Campbell County, the state,
and this is exactly the same thing we're
doing now. And I believe that the uh the
county and the city people are doing
exactly that. Setting up the parameters
to not hurt the land, the water, what we
have here, which we honor so well.
The uh I I just can't tell you how
important it is. I see the jobs here.
This is really a cool thing to see these
people come and talk about their
families. This is what we have talked
about for how many years? We don't have
jobs for our kids. This is our play. We
absolutely have to do that. I I I just
want to say the moratorum is not right.
A lot of time is said past SA
headquarters. A lot of time in the
Pentagon. You want to just push
something down the road moratorum. Or
why don't we go get a uh a consultant
and pay them $500,000 and they'll not
tell us anything. We don't already know
today. the moratorum. We wait a year.
We're not going to learn anything
different. This is what we've had. Thank
you for the city employees, the county
employees. You're doing a good job.
Thank you for doing this.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> My name is Ben Marley. I live in the
county and I have a there are two types
of data centers. One is based on AI. The
other is u crypto mining.
I live about a mile and a half from a
crypto mining facility.
And when I put my one good ear down to
the pillow at night, I can hear that
thing because sound not only travels
through the air, it travels through the
ground as well. I know that because I
was a sonman on a on a ship on a Navy
destroyer.
um travels through water as well.
I am I I'm all for this moratorum
partly for what the gentleman just just
said. We need time to set the
guidelines. I don't see any guidelines
that have been set so far by the county
or the city. They're just out there
looking for the jobs, looking for the
the tax revenue that they're going to
get off of it. But where are the
guidelines? We need time to set the
guidelines.
Um the
the water
is of definite concern. They say that
the the water and these uh
self-contained units will last six to
seven years. However, they will also
admit that every 3 to six months it has
to be refreshed because it does build up
contaminants within it because it has to
have chemicals in it in order to do the
efficient cooling.
So, where does that water go? We already
have a known decreasing water table in
Laram County.
If we're going to pump millions and
millions of gallons more for these GA
data centers, where is what's that going
to do to our water table?
Then the data centers also produce a lot
of heat.
Warm air at the ground level will
prevent rainfall because when you see
clouds in and we just saw it in this
beginnings of this storm that we're in
right now when you have high altitude
clouds dropping the water that
evaporates long before it hits the
ground. If we keep building data centers
and the latest number I've heard is that
there were 73 confirmed planned so far
in this county and it may go over a 100.
Take the effect of the 12 that are there
now apply it multiply it by seven that's
73.
Thank you.
>> Thank you sir.
>> Hello. Oh, that was my son husband that
was just here. I have a small thing to
say that could become very
>> Could you identify yourself, please?
>> Yes. My name is Nancy Marley. I live
here out on camp stool. This was my
husband that just spoke. I have a small
thing to say that might be very large.
I've been waking up at night because I
can't hear. I mean, because I can't
sleep. There's a some kind of kind of
noise that is coming through my bedroom
window. It's from these data centers.
the one that's near us. If we have 70 of
those around, do you guys think you're
going to get to sleep?
I don't think so. We need this
moratorum. We don't know what the hell
we're doing.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Thank you. I'm Richard Lyall. I live in
the I'm icon, right? I live in the
Western Hills area. I'm oppo I have no
uh financial interest in any uh
potential data center but I am opposed
to this moratorum because it is not
going to stop or regulate the collection
of personal data or the processing of
data or the storage of personal data.
Artificial intelligence is taking huge
amounts of raw data and processing it
mathematically
and coming out with information. One
application is facial recognition uh
programming.
There is a private company clearview AI.
They have last I heard 15 billion facial
images in their database. that's in the
cloud. The cloud is actually in a data
center. Uh law enforcement pays their
primary customer is law enforcement and
they have made thousands of arrests have
been made using their data. Now the same
type of technology is being used in
China and I don't like the way they use
it in China. There are four cities
including Shanghai and Beijing where
facial recognition uh is used to get on
a subway or a train. You don't have to
flash a card or put money in a toll box.
They've got your face and it's
automatically deducted from your bank
account. They have cameras all over that
track people and it's part of their way
to control people and they have a social
credit system that determines whether
you get an apartment, a job or kids get
school. Um, and that's China's use of
AI. But to protect us, we need the
technology and the human beings who
control it to be here. Um
Kroger uses AI extensively.
They've their uh net profit last year
from sales of everything from groceries
to pharmacy to gas was about $4.9
billion.
Of that 1 bill350
million came from data sales.
Another company Google. You think it's
really nice that you can Google for free
and learn anything. Um you can use a
Gmail or Chrome.
Well, how does Google make its money?
We've got a I want that to be done here
where we can legislate it and and
>> Thank you, Mr. Lyall.
>> Oh, I am
>> sorry. Goes fast, doesn't it?
>> Thank you for listening.
>> Thank you.
>> Go ahead.
>> Good afternoon. My name is Tony
Fichchek. Um, president of Ward One. Um,
I'm not going to keep repeating the same
things we keep hearing over and over
tonight. I'm just going to kind of hit
on the fact that a single data center
brings on average around400 to500
million in capital investment, millions
in annual property tax revenue, and
hundreds of permanent high wage jobs in
operations, engineering, security, plus
thousands of the construction jobs
during the build phase. That uh really
just kind of equates to a stronger tax
base for our schools, our roads, and
public safety. Anybody that's been down
south gley, you see all the abandoned
buildings and uh rundown trailer parks
and all that. We could really use this
money and by putting a moratorium on it,
as a gentleman said earlier, these
companies won't wait. They'll pick up.
They'll go somewhere else and we could
really use this tax revenue. Um that's
pretty much all I have.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Hello, Mario Cordova, 49year resident.
Just want to touch on the fact that
people believe that they can't get these
jobs and they're not for locals. I think
>> just like to touch on the fact that
people believe that these jobs are
unobtainable. They're out there if
you're a skilled crafts and skilled
tradesman, carpenter, electrician,
whatever, they are out there for the
locals as well. Been out there with no
problems and it's a very good blessing
for our family. I mean, as far as I
worked on the capital project and that
was when the union came back again, the
carpenter union. And after that project
was done, then a lot of people had to
either travel out of town for their job
or else leave the union. Now it's back
and that's a great opportunity for all
of us now back in here in our backyard.
So thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Hello. Why me? I'm extremely nervous.
>> You're okay.
>> Um well, I'm going to be a little bit
selfish here because I'm going to talk
about myself and my personal family.
>> Excuse me, sir. What's your name? My
name is Orlando Martinez out of war II.
Um, I'm going to talk about my family.
I drove a 100 miles to come here because
my family is still in Colorado. I've
been a resident, um, a state resident
for over a year and a half. And I
finally was able to obtain a loan from a
bank so I could own a house or or buy a
house over by Dildine. Dildine's where
my son's registered to go to school next
year. And I was very excited to have him
bring my family up here and to find out
that might take a pause and stuff like
that. That's a huge huge it would be
detrimental to my family to stop for an
entire year. What do I do? I specialize
in well helping all my carpenter
brothers right here safely build
projects and data centers and stuff like
that. And I've been doing it for a while
and I was proud to move to the state of
Wyoming. I didn't I'm tired of just
coming up here to fish. I like fishing
up here. I've been fishing up here for
20 some years. But it all a lot of these
studies can be done. These studies can
be done and ongoing and they could
start. Nobody's trying to stop them
completely stopping everything. I've
seen the grounds already cut in quite a
few data centers. They're going to be
going for years. If that's the ground
state, if the dirt's cut, they're going.
So, thank you for listening to me. I'm a
a proud Cheyenne resident and looking
forward to my family moving up here at
the end of the school season in
Colorado.
>> Thank you, sir. And Dildine Dolphins are
a great school. That's where my kids
went. So, congratulations,
>> Mr. McKay.
>> Madam Chair, Renie McKay, I'm the
president of the Wyoming Business
Alliance and I'm from Ward One. Thanks a
lot for your your time today. The
Wyoming Business Alliance represents um
every industry in Wyoming, members from
every industry or private organization.
um they're from every corner of Wyoming
and every size of business. And so that
really kind of makes us uh very
interested in this entire conversation
because our members are rateayers as
well. So if anybody is concerned about
rateayers, the biggest rateayers in
Wyoming are the businesses of Wyoming.
So they are the ones who are most
focused on that because it drives their
business decisions. Um and really as the
business alliance for all of them, we're
concerned about economic prosperity. And
that was great to just hear because the
reason I do this work is so folks can be
here and have their kids here so my kids
have an opportunity to to um live in
Cheyenne to have a job here that can
sustain them so they can afford a house.
Um and so this is important and uh I
think as you look back at the data
center conversation, this has been going
on for decades. Um it was in the '9s um
when Governor Garinger tried to help get
the fiber optic companies to have POPs
here in this county so that Wyoming
companies and industries could come here
and access the fiber that goes through
Wyoming and that opportunity. Then try
to attract the ENCAR computer to have
that supercomput here to show that
Wyoming can have technology as part of
its industries. Um, and then in the uh
2010s, we start to actually try to get
into the tax uh climate so that data
centers can come here and choose Wyoming
over other places. So, this has been a
long time in the in the making and I'm
really excited to see where we are
because this is a really enormous
opportunity for Wyoming. I do think
obviously this moment creates big
questions and I think we're having a
really good conversation because no
one's asking a question that isn't
appropriate to have a discussion about.
Um I certainly was glad to hear at the
last water meeting that there were
independent experts from UW from the
state engineers office who were talking
about how um the impacts are managed and
are regulated well in Wyoming and are
minimal. Our our agriculture in this
county uses more than 10 times as much
water. You were talking um huge amounts
more than data centers ever would. And
that's a really important part of
Wyoming to have our agricultural economy
here. So thank you for that. The other
thing I'll just say is is that these
jobs are needed. Um employment is down
in this county this year. Um so if
you're looking at what's going on with
the economy, we do need more taxpayers
and more employers here. So this is an
important moment and I really hope um
you'll oppose this moratorum. But I do
really appreciate that people value you
all and the city staff as those
independent uh voices that can provide
answers as we move forward. So thanks
for taking this on, but thanks for for
trying to take on that prosperity for
our kids, too. Thank you.
>> Hi.
>> Hello. My name is Aaron Larson. I'm from
Ward One and I'm with the IBW Local 415.
Um, members of the council, putting a
moratorium on data centers generates the
exact kind of chaos and uncertainty that
deters critical investments in our
community. We shouldn't be hitting the
pause button, but instead we should be
setting the standard.
We need a strategy that supports good
union jobs and builds resilient supply
chains right here at home. Without
strong labor standards on these massive
projects, we risk a race to the bottom
on both wages and safety. That is how we
protect our workers and bring real value
to this town. Let's reject the
moratorum, reject the race to the
bottom, and demand high road union jobs
instead.
>> Thank you, Mr. Larson.
Hello, Representative.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman. Uh Gary
Brown, House Citric 41 representative
and resident in Ward One.
So, we've heard that there's a lot of
misinformation out there. And I agree
there is, but a lot of it is because
we're being uh a lot of information is
being hid from us. I had a whistleblower
come for me who was working out at the
data centers. We've been told we're
going to have 40 of them. Then we hear
we're going to have 70 of them. The
whistleblower tells me we're going to
have over 130 of them.
So, we do have misinformation
and information that a lot of people
here have and are not giving us.
We talk about the water
and we talk in acre feet. An acre foot
of water is 325,900
gallons.
And when you start looking at the normal
size data centers,
if you're just a closed loop system,
it's going to hold over 300,000
gallons of water and you have that that
many data centers. Now, we're talking up
into the hundreds and hundreds of
millions of gallons of water. But then I
started talking to people in other
states, people in Virginia, people in
Ohio, people in Georgia, in Texas, and
they have the closed loop system, but
they tell me, "No, it does not stay in
there for six or seven years. Stays in
there for 3 to six months, and then they
have to change it." So, we're not being
given information and we're being given
false information.
We see a lot of people here today, but
we don't see nearly the members the
number of people that we could have
here. I have a petition here that has
space for over 64 signatures.
I filled three of these in less than a
week.
So, we have a lot of people working that
can't be here, but the community is not
happy about this. Thank you.
Thank you, sir.
>> Good afternoon, Madam Chair. Betsy Hail,
CEO of Cheyenne Leads, former resident
of Ward One and now resident of Laramie
County. Um, I guess I'll try to um not
be held totally to these numbers, but
we've heard a lot of numbers today that
I think we probably ought to get
straight. And so currently in Cheyenne,
we have 10 data centers, what we'll
call, and I'll do a definition here
shortly, that are actually operational.
We have five that are under
construction, and we have eight that
have either been planned, announced, or
in some sort of development review
process with the city or the county. Why
are the differences in numbers? So,
you've heard 70, you've heard 130,
you've heard 40 43. Well, there's a lot
of different sources for data center
information. You can go online.
Everybody goes online, right? All the
Googling that goes on and you can find
uh so-called expert websites that'll
show you the number 43. I believe that
was a number that came out in January.
You can then take maps that you see on
the county's website. You can take maps
that you see on the city's website. You
can merge those maps with that 43 and
you can pretty quickly get to 70. And so
I think what needs to happen is some
kind of a specific repository. The
numbers that I just shared with you 10,
five, and 8 are physical data center
locations here in Cheyenne and proposed
in Laramie County. And so I think that's
really important that we get down to
some real numbers, tangible boots on the
ground. The other thing I want to point
out is that this idea that there's some
kind of government loophole or
regulatory loophole by putting data
centers in business parks is a real
falsehood. It's actually harder to go
into a business park because we do have
commercial owners associations. So they
self police themselves on the types of
uses that they have and you heard about
things like outdoor storage. There's
also conditions, covenants, and
restrictions. There's annual
assessments. And so while an industrial
sightings permit process is a great
idea, the ongoing oversight and I have a
staff person on my staff who weekly goes
into these four business parks that we
manage our own and they will actually
look to see where there might be
problems. In fact, last week we received
notice from a county commissioner that
there was some light casting going on at
the Bison Business Park. We were able to
reach out to Microsoft and to the
contractor and get that issue addressed.
And so what I want to make sure we do is
we don't get all emotional about what's
going on in other places regarding data
centers and we start to look at what's
really going on here. So thank you
again. Cheyenne leads opposes this
moratorum.
>> Thank you Miss Hail,
Mr. Brown.
>> Thank you Madam Chair and uh members of
the committee. Exy Brown Ward two. Now,
I'm not going to I'm my concerns are
just as much as anybody else's as far as
the water, the power, and all that stuff
that uh I'm not going to belabor on
that, but I am going to bring up a point
that I think that has not been brought
up uh with the exception of uh
Councilman Moody is what is the
vulnerability from a national security
standpoint when you do cluster all of
these data centers in one area. You
know, when I used to do indust uh
infrastructure and security and stuff in
the Air Force, we had to look at where
we're putting our assets and how they
were going to be secured and where
they're going to be most vulnerable and
how to protect them against
vulnerabilities.
And when you cluster a bunch of the same
items like these data centers, your risk
of vulnerability goes way up. And why
can these not be spread out further and
other areas? We have a lot of wide open
space here in Wyoming.
And so that's uh one aspect uh that I'm
really concerned about. Uh second is I'm
all about growth, but I'm about
responsible growth.
We've already had county planners or
city planners that talked in previous
meetings that said these are building
faster than they can plan for them.
And we've already proved with some folks
already proved with the previous
comments in just uh some of the earlier
items today that there's not really a
lot of good strategic planning and that
the the development is going faster than
the planning is happening. So we got to
make sure that we are able to plan and
this moratorum will allow us the
opportunity and allow your city
planners, your staff to be able to plan
for the future growth of Wyoming because
if we don't plan for the future growth
of Wyoming or for Cheyenne, what's going
to happen is we're going to be locked in
by data centers and the expansion and
the growth of this city is going to be
restricted. So thank you for your time.
Appreciate it as always.
Hi,
>> good good afternoon, madame chair and
committee. I'm Ariana Aguilar, Ward One.
I am here um with my brothers and
sisters from local 1271.
Um I am opposed to this. Um,
I joined the union straight out of high
school, um, in search for a job, for a
new opportunity. And the job that they
put me out on was out on the, um, new
data center. I, a lot of my family, my
mother is here and so is my uncle.
They've also worked out there. I have
cousins and and my aunt who also works
out there. This is a very big job for a
lot of us. It provides income. Um our
union provided apprenticeships for us
new um uh new laborers. Um
um
sorry. Um I was able to get a lot of
certifications, equipment training um
out of this job. I think I've gained a
lot of experience from it. I've been
able to start a college fund for myself.
I make I made more than at least $24 an
hour. I have insurance. I think that if
we were to put a pause in this um this
job, a lot of people will lose income.
They will lose insurance and a lot of us
depend on it. I understand a lot of the
concerns that are being shared today.
It's a valid concern. I very much
understand it. But I think we also need
to consider our workforce and those that
are on the job doing the work. And a lot
of these people are searching for second
chances for an income for support and
all that. especially younger generations
where we're have we're facing a lot of
um um like uh there's a lot of
unemployment and this is a great way for
us younger people to start finding our
way to start finding jobs and I think
this was a great g gateway for me and
many I have co-workers who also my age
who came straight out of high school
looking for the same opportunities as
me. So
>> thank you
M repres
you did great.
Representative Singh.
>> Thank you, Madam Chairman, and members
of the committee. Uh my name is Daniel
Singh. I represent House District 61 and
I live in Ward 3. Um I'm not here today
to tip the scale one way or another. Uh
if a moratorum is adopted, it gives us
12 months to talk about the issue, kick
the can down the road and uh try to
figure out exactly what it is that the
public wants uh when it comes to a
plethora of issues from uh environmental
quality, electric rates, and uh water
usage. And so I I wanted to acknowledge
and frankly agree with what the mayor
had to say that some of these some of
these things aren't in the
municipalities
um perview. Um and as I'm listening to
the conversation today and I'm really
grateful for the discussion and the uh
community input, I'm seeing the
potential for amendments in title 35 as
it relates to the department of
environmental quality, uh title 37 with
the public service commission and title
41 with the state engineers office. Um
and so uh whether or not there is a
moratorum uh I do think that there are
opportunities to adequately address the
situation and the problems at hand in a
way that is more broad than just for the
city of Cheyenne. And I'm grateful for
uh I'm glad that we're having this
opportunity to to talk about this issue
here in Cheyenne because uh the rest of
the communities really look for Cheyenne
and follow our lead. And so, um,
I, yeah, I'm just grateful for that. I
also just wanted to acknowledge that,
uh, personal data and biometric data
came up as an issue that people were
concerned about earlier. And, uh, just
know that you're in the legislature that
your select committee on blockchain,
financial technology, and digital
innovation technology is going to be
taking that up as a uh, issue on June
15th and 16th in Sheridan. and I welcome
the public to be a part of that
conversation. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Hi.
>> Hello. Uh my name is Christopher Nino um
Ward One and I'm opposed to the
moratorum. Um there are some there are a
lot of very real and legitimate concerns
to any given community that can be
associated with um data centers. The
chief among them we've gone over I think
today quite a bit. power, you know,
impacts to rateayers, water consumption,
pollution, um, lots of many different
kinds of recognizable externalities that
lots of different types of businesses
have to be concerned with. Um, I think
Cheyenne and Larry County have done an
exceptionally good job of managing those
externalities, much better than other
cities and counties that I've looked
into. Um, I think there could be some
more communication in regards to that.
It's strange to me that so many people
seem to think that they're that
rateayers have been negatively impacted
by these data centers when from my
research it appears kind of somewhat to
be the opposite. Maybe true. Um but I
think a lot of the support for this
moratorum is coming from a place coming
from concerns with data centers and data
technology in general and not their
impact or usage in the community. um and
this isn't really the venue to try to
push back against uh those kinds of
concerns and it would be terribly
equipped to even make an effort in that
regard. Um so I think that those things
should probably not be um considered
when it comes to a mortorium on data
centers here. Um,
and also
I mean there there's a lot of
misinformation misinformation that's
kind of take been impacting this
conversation like people mentioned Elon
Musk putting data centers in space that
can't happen. The thermodynamics make
that impossible. Um, so that's not like
a but um I think it would be very
beneficial for there to be some sort of
communication campaign to try to explain
and work with the community so they
understand the actual impacts. Um,
things like the sound impact that
there's sound affecting residents.
That's something that I haven't heard
until today that should definitely be
looked into. Um, but I think that that
would require a totally different
approach from just a blanket ban or or a
temporary ban on any type of business.
Um, I don't think that a moratorum is a
is a delicate or selective enough
instrument to address any of the
concerns associated with data centers.
Um, and I don't think that putting a
12-month pause is going to benefit
anybody involved in in the community or
in the in the industry. Thank you.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Good afternoon, Madam Chair, council
members. Uh, my name is Tyler Gibbs,
lifelong resident of Wyoming. uh energy
manager for Microsoft Corporation
located here in Cheyenne. Still have
family ranch in northern Wyoming. Um
live in Ward 2 here in Cheyenne. And
just wanted to start by saying um we
Microsoft really appreciate community
support we've had and we hope we've been
a good member of the community community
over the last 15 years. Uh and we plan
to be a good community member for many
years to come.
You'll notice that we are uh generally
uh very transparent. Everything we do is
under Microsoft Corporation. Um and and
I like working for an organization that
uh is transparent like that.
Some of my background here in Cheyenne.
Um
as I mentioned, I've been local here for
about 10 years. I've been on the board
at Meals on Wheels of Cheyenne for a
four-year term. currently uh serving on
the board at the Children's Museum and
my day-to-day role entails solving the
energy needs of the data centers which
as you all know is complex but something
I just want to highlight is that
starting every conversation that we have
talking about energy uh and electricity
the the top priority something that's
always top of mind we have to make sure
whatever we do doesn't impact customer
rates that's if there's anything we do
that's trying to devi de deviate from
that. We have to find a way to make up
for it and make sure we won't impact
other customer rates. I'll let Black
Hills Energy talk a little more about
some of the specific tariffs that have
been put in place to ensure rateayer
protection, namely the large power
contract service, but there are also
more uh that will come. Uh one thing I
also want to highlight is just the
community benefit from all the energy
that and electricity the data centers
use. One thing that's not spoke of very
much is sales tax and franchise fees on
electricity. Would highly encourage the
council to look at uh the franchise fees
collected in the North Range Business
Park um in 2025 and beyond after it was
annexed in December of 24. Uh Microsoft
was fully supportive of that annexation
and paying the franchise fee to the
city.
I also want to just highlight that um
the state of Wyoming is a net exporter
of electricity. Sales tax on electricity
is paid in the state in which it's
consumed. Um so something else to be
mindful of and why not pay more sales
tax to have that electricity consumed
here in our beautiful state. Lastly, I
want to welcome everyone here and anyone
else in the community. Microsoft will be
having a community engagement event at
LC
uh Flex Tech building May 28th at 5:30
PM until 8:30 p.m. and all of our
subject matter experts will be there to
answer uh any questions that the
community has.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Thank you.
>> Hi. Turn on the microphone, please.
I'm used to calling for the back 40.
>> As everyone can tell, I am old.
>> Ma'am, what's your name?
>> Nancy Sunday. And I was born in Wyoming
and I've been here for 83 years. And in
that length of time,
I have seen many, many changes. A lot of
them aren't for better. When I was a
child, we had running water. We ran out
and we pumped it and we ran back in.
Um, so I learned at a very early age to
be very conservative with water and I
still am.
And water is for Wyoming especially and
other places in this world the blood of
life. I looked it up and it says that
you can live for three minutes without
oxygen.
You can live for 5 days without water.
You can live from three to 14 weeks
without food.
But you cannot
drink
data and you cannot grow food
on data.
And so my
uh suggestion would be to think about
what is really necessary
and what really will keep us alive and
what we're passing on to a future
generation. Are they going to have
water? Are they going to have food?
There will probably be more wars fought
over the lack of water and food than
anything else, not data.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Good afternoon, council members. Uh
David Bush here on behalf of Black Hills
Energy, uh resident of Ward 2.
Is that better? Uh resident of W 2. Um
wanted to touch on the electricity side
today. There's been a lot of
conversation around that. Um, as has
been stated, Black Hills Energy, we
serve the electricity and natural gas
needs of our customers here in in
Cheyenne. Uh, we serve natural gas
through uh quite a bit of Wyoming,
actually the eastern like half of
Wyoming. So, um, electricity here has
been something that's been talked about
a lot with data centers. Um,
we, uh, we have, as has been mentioned,
the large power contract service tariff.
Uh it's basically a contract. Sometimes
people get confused when they hear the
word tariff and think we're talking
about taxes like international trade
kind of stuff, but it's a contract that
we have under that tariff. Uh the uh
users of that tariff are primarily data
centers. Uh we designed that tariff um
for Microsoft when they came back in
2012. It is under Wyoming statute
373116.
uh that tariff requires that those uh
users bring all the money that they need
and and pay for everything that goes
into the power that they require for
their facilities. Um the benefit of that
is uh built into that contract uh which
was also reviewed by the Wyoming Public
Service Commission, the experts in
utility rate making in the state and
also the office of consumer advocate who
are uh that that's the entity that uh
engages on behalf of all rateayers in
the state.
The um LPCS contract uh requires them to
pay for all of the infrastructure and
all the power that they need. That power
is generally uh comes from the grid
other than a smaller portion that is
paid for by them. That is us part of our
base um uh electricity that we provide.
So
they help pay for um the infrastructure
that's used for the city for the rest of
the rate payers. It's a benefit for our
rate payers in the city. Uh to the tune
of since 2022 about $2 million per year
has been a credit that has been put
towards rateayers bills here in the city
of Cheyenne. Uh we also have what's
called the blockchain interruptible
service tariff. That's a tariff that's
designed specifically for Bitcoin
miners. Um that basically says if if the
power is available, you get it. If it's
not available, you don't get it. That's
why it's called interruptible. We can
curtail them at any time we need to. Um
so the the number of the data centers
that we have is uh what Miss Hail spoke
to earlier. Um those numbers are what
we've seen. I don't know where 70 came
from, but uh as the electricity provider
providing service to these folks. Uh we
haven't seen anything about 70 um coming
to town. So with that, I'm happy to
answer any questions later on or um
provide any other further information.
>> Thank you, Mr. Bush.
Good afternoon. Um, madame chair,
council members, my name is Chris Tetlo.
I am the metro director for Microsoft uh
in Cheyenne, Wyoming. In other words,
I'm responsible for operating the three
campuses that Microsoft has out here
currently. Um, there's a lot of of
information that's going on around here.
What I wanted to give you was some
information about what we actually do
do. We do employ people from Cheyenne.
Um, somebody had mentioned it'd be great
if we did things with local schools to
help out. We absolutely do things with
with local schools and shame on us for
not being better at selling what those
things are that we do. Uh, when we came
out here, we developed a program with uh
Dr. Schaefer out at Larmy County
Community College called the data center
academy. The sole purpose of that is to
prepare people, and I'm not going to say
kids. I'm an older person. There are
people of every age that go through that
program, some of them looking to change
jobs. Uh, but it gets them ready to go
work in a data center on the IT side uh
of the fence. Um, we send people out to
talk to the Laramie County School
District. I have a a women in data
center program that I sponsor here in
Cheyenne. Uh, and we send some former
teachers that we have working for us out
to go talk to kids in the school and let
them know what kind of jobs we do have
in the data center. Some people are
fairly intimidated by the fact that
we're Microsoft and they don't think
they're ready to take these jobs on. We
we have a fairly robust training program
and we can uh bring people in with the
skill sets that get them going and train
them up to be good techs and whether
that takes them further with Microsoft
or another company uh it absolutely
gives them a job that pays well. It
gives them good benefits. And for kids
that may not have the opportunity to
have schooling paid for or have a grant,
we also offer to offer the opportunity
for employees to get tuition
reimbursement uh for for college. So
again, lots of information out there and
shame on us if we haven't done a good
job selling some of the things we do out
in the community. We will do better at
that. Um, but I am here opposed to the
moratorum because I believe we're going
to build more data centers out here.
We're going to bring great jobs to the
economy. And when I first came out here
12 years ago, relocated my family to
Cheyenne, I got the privilege of working
with Governor Me, then Governor Meade,
and one of his objectives he told me was
they want to get good paying jobs and
keep Cheyenne kids in Cheyenne if that's
what they want to do. And I think that's
exactly what we're doing. Thank you.
Thank you, sir.
>> Hi.
>> Yeah. Good afternoon, Madam Chairman and
Councilman. My name is Kristen Lee and I
am um with the related data center team.
I'm their uh person in Cheyenne that's
been hired by them. I'm an attorney with
Haway and Coons. I'm here today on
behalf of related to say we have so
appreciated the support of this
community um at the city level at at
every level of every group that they
have joined the Wyoming business
alliance leads every group has offered
such support. We will be open as a data
center um the first quarter of 2027. The
permanent jobs that will be at the data
center will be about 40. These are good
jobs, highpaying jobs. please look at
the website and see because they're
hiring. So, we oppose the moratorum, but
really I just wanted to say thank you
and thank you for bringing this
discussion forward. I think it's great
and I think the information here today
has just been great on both sides to
say, hey, it's a real learning for
everybody. The technology is getting so
much better and they're advancing in on
so many fronts. So, um and we're buying
electricity out of the Black Hills
tariff and really appreciated. Black
Hills has been such a great partner,
too. So, thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Go ahead.
>> Hi, my name is Gail Young. I'm from Ward
Three, and I just have a question about
the long-term planning of these uh data
centers. Um what is the longevity of
each of these data centers? Uh what is
the what are the plans for reclamation
when they go out of business? Uh we have
reclam reclamation plans for our coal
industries and other industries in uh
the state of Wyoming. What are the plans
when these gigantic buildings uh are no
longer being manned by anyone and are no
longer in business. So I'm I'm for a
moratorum at this time.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Hi.
>> Hello. Can you hear me? Hi. Uh, my name
is Nicholas Clark. I was born and raised
here. Um, I'm against the moratorum.
Just just due to the simple fact that,
you know, techn is coming. You know, we
can't stop it. We can't change it.
Exactly. Like, you know, Chuck said,
it's it's a good opportunity to take.
You know, I have four kids of my own,
and it's something that my kids look
forward to me doing. You know, I get to
drive by a building and say, "Hey guys,
look, I've I've been on the crew to help
build these things." you know, and my
little four-year-old, he's cool. He
always puts on my heart hat. He's just
like, "Dad, I want to be just like you."
And so, you know, I raised on the old
school values of, you know, family, you
know, God and family. That's that's what
I live by. And I want to try to do
whatever I can to be the best father I
can for my kids. And you know, without a
job, you know, a lot of construction, a
lot of people don't realize that
construction, it's not consistent work.
You know, 12 months, it it really is an
eternity, especially if we're drywallers
or framers. Different crews, okay, the
the framing goes up first. Once that's
done, they move on to the next job or,
you know, they go start drywalling. Once
the drywall is done, it's done and over.
Then you got the painters come and do
the finishing work. But you know having
that break would would not be beneficial
at all. You know we we need the work to
sustain
livelihood really. You know exactly what
these guys said. We got good paying jobs
but it's also a career something that we
need in this town. You know I've done a
lot of the base work. I laid a lot of
the concrete for these um power lines
that came in before the data centers
even got built. And so it's a foundation
that starts somewhere, but to continue
on with it is something that we need.
And uh I hope that you guys would
consider to not close it. So thank you
guys.
>> Thank you.
>> Hi. Uh welcome. My name is Alex Bowler.
Maybe you see me in print and some of
the uh capital
capital whatever it is that they Anyway,
I'm I'm in favor of this uh data
centers. I would like to remind you
folks that this uh moratorum
uh ordinance does not apply to uh data
centers that are under construction or
have broken ground. That means that the
12 or 14 data centers that we currently
have in progress or in operation, it
does this ordinance does not apply to
them. It applies to the the data centers
that are thinking about coming to
Cheyenne and to Laram County. I have uh
I've I've taken the liberty of
forwarding this ordinance in its draft
form to our county commissioners with
the hope that they will
uh create something similar and protect
us all. There's a there's a lot of good
reasons for this moratorum. It's a a
huge issue. It's vastly misunderstood
and I I I want to say it again. It
doesn't apply to the 12 or 14 data
centers that are currently operational
or under construction. It applies to
future data center people.
>> Thank you, sir.
>> Okay.
Okay.
Anyone else in the room before we go to
online?
I don't know if she's moving or leaving.
We're going through everybody. Yeah.
>> So, um, okay. Jennifer online.
>> Donnie Courier, you should be able to
unmute yourself.
>> Yes. Thank you. Can you guys hear me?
Okay.
>> Yes, sir, we can.
>> Okay. Thank you, madam uh chair and city
council. First, I want to say um Donnie
Carrer, Ward 3, and I'm calling in
because I couldn't make it there today.
I want to give a special thanks to
Councilman Mark Moody for taking the
time to put this together. Um I know
that it's a very uh debatable, heated
thing on both sides, but uh that's the
kind of stuff that is a is just a
regular person we look for with our U
council people and elected officials.
So, thank you, Mr. Moody, for that cuz
this in no way is a shot at anything.
But given all of what I've heard today,
um, and then just doing a little
research myself and, um, whatnot, I'm
going to actually say that I don't want
this, um, to pass. Um, I I I'm actually
listening to the voices of the other
people that have, um, expressed a huge
concern in regards to, you know, the
impact that it has in their lives, and
their family. And I I think that no
matter what, we should always be rooted
in being factual. But there's no doubt
um every time I wake up and I'm jumping
on social media, there is so much non
there there's so much misinformation
that's being spread out there that I
believe that if we would take as a
community and take a little self-
responsibility and say, "Hey, let's look
at the facts here. Let's let's take our
eyes off of the negative um and and
let's actually go to facts." You know, I
would think that um as much as that the
water issue, the usage of all these
things that would be so prominent, if
it's true, we would see that in other
communities. I started browsing um other
states um Facebook pages just to see if
there was an overwhelming report of all
these things. And you want to know what
I found? Hardly nothing. Um does it take
away from the people that have a
concern? There's nothing wrong with
that. But these people are really um
they're working here. They're coming to
our communities. And I also want to give
a shout out to um Councilwoman Michelle
Aldrich. She brought up a an excellent
point and everybody knows that um I've
been to a couple of these meetings where
I've spoke against council and the
mayor, but this time I'm sorry. I'm
going to roll with you guys on this one.
Um Councilwoman Michelle Aldridge is
correct. We cry on one hand that we
don't have the jobs here. We we're we're
literally being hypocrites. And I'm not
saying that to be disrespectful to
anybody that is going to hear this, but
there's no evidence that would say that
anything is is going to stop um these
data centers that are bad. I mean, I
think we need to put aside this this
fear-mongering and concentrate on the
facts. Um and there's just no
overwhelming um you know, stuff to me
that would say that these things are
bad. Now, I'm not going to lie and say
that I want any of these things here cuz
I don't. With that being said, we have
to work as a community. We need to be
here. And this is just kind of something
funny I'm going to throw out there. I
know that I was talking to some friends
of mine. There's a lot of business
opportunities out there, too. Um, you
know, I think we have realators out
here. We have people that can benefit
from this. We're always so concentrated
on the negative, the negative, negative.
We forget that AI does a lot of good.
Um, but it's up to the people to find
those things and and to look for them.
But I know talking to some people about,
you know, even like selling property.
You know, we have a a woman Kathy
Skidiano that stepped up in there that
is a community member that she's out
there um doing all these things. She's a
realtor. If these people want to know
from a realtor perspective, give this
woman a call. But don't give up talking
to your council members. Don't demonize
each other.
>> Mr. Career,
>> thank you.
>> Who else do we have? Uh Mr. Stewart, you
should be able to unmute yourself.
>> And thank you. Um, my name is Sean
Stewart. I'm resident of Ward 3. I'm
speaking against the moratorum. Um, just
quickly, uh, I've been in the the
technology industry for most of my adult
life, um, including data center
management. Prior to that, I worked in
the power industry. Um, the reason I'm I
want to speak against this is I think,
uh, and it was eloquently put earlier,
um, if we don't build them here, they
will go somewhere else. And this is a
race. Uh like it or not, we are
competing um not just within the United
States and in other states, but we are
competing globally for these resources.
Uh data centers are here to stay. AI is
unfortunately here to stay whether you
like it or not. Um so do we want to reap
the benefits of of that buildout and the
ongoing operation of it? Um and you
know, speaking kind of the the trade
position, sorry, my thoughts aren't well
organized. I should have written
something down. Um
but uh you know even once the
construction on these facilities is
complete they are complex machines. They
require ongoing maintenance. Um it's not
just the staff members who are
maintaining the the uh servers and stuff
inside the facility but you've got
electricians have to come out to
maintain the power systems the the
filtration systems. All of that is
ongoing. It may not be the 5,000
employees you have at the beginning but
it it is an impact to the community. And
I think ultimately the the benefits
outweigh
um some of the detriment especially you
know these systems are got a lot more
efficient over the last 20 years. I've
seen it personally. Um companies do not
get in the business to waste money so
they are going to make these as cheap
and efficiently as possible.
Thank you.
>> Thank you sir. Anyone else online?
Okay. I know there was a couple of
people that wanted to add something
else, but please make if it's something
that's already been said, let's not go
there because I think we've gone there.
So if you have something different that
we missed.
>> Thank you, Madam Chair. I just want to
say that all of these questions and
everybody said really great things. The
the the thing that bothers me the most
is that whether we have a moratorum or
not, these questions still need to be
answered. We still need to get this
information. And I hear, you know, I
don't want these people to lose their
jobs either, but we still need these. It
shouldn't be a moratorum or not. And
just for FYI, um the uh Wyoming Business
Council and the Wyoming Outdoor Council
white paper does say that these data
centers, as long as they're located in
um county designated business parks, are
exempt from the uh industrial sighting.
>> Thank you, ma'am.
>> Heather Mad again. Um, I have I have a
lot of compassion for the people who are
working on these things. I I love that
people are making money and able to
afford homes. Sounds like for the first
time. I love it. Um, I'm concerned
though that these data centers are
paying well above market market rates,
you know, market salaries. And when
construction does stop because it
eventually it will whether it's
moratorum or not. What is going to
happen to the people who have become
dependent on these six figure salaries?
Um are there going to be businesses for
them to return to because data centers
are going on construction sites and
poaching local business
um workers? Uh I just worry that you
know that's inflating the the real
estate market and again when this boom
ends where are people going to be able
to afford this lifestyle they've become
accustomed to over years of having this
inflated income? Will they leave and
follow the work like what they've said,
you know, have been what I've been
hearing so often is what they've been
forced to do. Um, I just worry that this
is a false inflation of our economy and
that it won't be sustainable when this
boom busts.
>> Thank you.
>> Do you have something new? Okay.
>> Oh, okay. Hi, I'm Schnea. I'm with the
Labor Local Tower 71. Um, that is always
a concern, you know, a bus and a boom.
Uh, one thing that you look around,
you'll see all these union members here
and we're all local. So, what happens
when we when work ends? We move with the
work but we stayed local. So our income
actually stays here. We still spend
money. Our family still still spends
money here. So that is something that
why if you notice you'll see a lot of us
always show up to the industrial
sighting. And so we keep our Wyoming
work, our Wyoming work, so that it
increases the money and everything
that's spent here locally and not from
Coloradoans coming in. No offense to our
fellow Colorado and we we still love
you, but we want to keep our money here.
We want to our our society to grow um
also with the money that's increased. So
we have I don't know if a lot of people
are familiar with prevailing wage. Um
what we do what that does is it takes
what the local amount of money the the
average is ours is usually a little bit
higher. So we increase the amount of
money that that people make setting a
standard for other people in our trade.
The average money that another laborer
makes that's non-union is about $16 to
$17 an hour. We make $28 an hour. That
increases the cost. It doesn't increase
the the the
technical amount of what companies are
willing to pay for bids. It just closes
that gap between what Microsoft is
making and what we're making. Um, the
big reason why you see a lot of us union
members here right now supporting this
is because right now these data centers
are going union. In 12 months, can we
guarantee that they're going to be
union? We can't. But right now, we can
make sure that money is kept local.
What's going to happen in 12 months when
they have that chance to rebid them and
that other stuff? So, that's why we come
to our community asking for this support
is because it's needed. They're going to
be built. There's no doubt about it.
They are going to be built. The point
is, are they going to be built with
safety, with workers in mind? Are they
going to be built with somebody making
$16 an hour not having any type of
medical or dental or anything like that?
And those people that they bring in from
other states will go home. So, we will
get that boom and that bust if we let
these non-union companies come in and
take our work. Thank you for your time.
>> Thank you. Some Oh, we're not doing that
still. Oh, never mind. Do you have
something new, Kathy?
>> Yeah, I wanted to Kathy Sigiano. Um, I
wanted to address the I I think it was
Microsoft, the gentleman that was here
talking about how they are going into
the schools. Um, I did not know they
were going into the schools and the high
schools. So, I think they definitely
need to advertise that more. Um, get
that out into the community. I would
love to be your representative to help
you with that. Um, but I I was just
talking to one of the workers in the
hallway and I appreciate her being here
speaking. I appreciate again all of them
here speaking because we need the
information from the locals. You know, I
there is a lot of misinformation out
there about not having local people
working here. I mean, I'm a huge I I
support local as often as I possibly
can. So, if the local people who live
here are getting these jobs, I'm all for
that, but I will say the misinformation
that's been out there about the 40 or
70, you you need to find a way to kibash
that because people are freaking out.
And I think if we knew more information,
it goes back to just information. We
need the information. So, I appreciate
it. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
>> Do you have something new?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. and environmental impact reports.
>> Okay.
>> So, um I don't know much about what's
been done on the environmental impact
reports in this community. So, if people
are looking for more information,
they're very comprehensive documents.
You might want to look at those. There's
public hearings on those usually public
input. Um they address all kinds of
things besides just environment. They
traffic, the noise, the pollution, um
the air pollution. So um I think that
this this moratorum is an interesting
conundrum because we're already doing
studies look at the environmental impact
reports and I don't know what this
moratorium is going to be doing as far
as bringing new studies forth. I haven't
heard any proposals on any new studies.
So whether or not it gets passed I think
that might be something to look at of
what new independent studies and by the
way environmental impact reports are
independent. They're done by consulting
companies. So there's no usual there's
no bias in them. So again just I think
we need to be paying more attention to
those and there's probably available
online and when a new um company is
looking to build her there would be an
environmental impact report being put
together. So again that would be an
indication of how many companies are
looking to be building here. So just
thought
>> point of information chairwoman uh are
are you Ryan?
>> Okay. I'm just trying to find your name
on my list so I can make and make that
note. Thanks.
>> Thank you sir. Do you have something
new?
>> Yes. Okay. Thank you, Madam Chairman.
Gary Brown, representative House
District 41 and and resident of Ward
One. U Mr. Bush had said earlier that he
didn't know where the number 70 came
from. Um that number came from
Councilman uh Wolf at a coffee on the in
W one. So that's where the number 70
came from was from a city councilman.
>> Thank you, sir.
Okay, Mr. Moody, would you like to close
us down for our last public comment?
>> I will close it down. Thank you, Madam
Chair.
A lot of good discussion here. Still say
needs to uh pass. Let's put in this
perspective here just for comparison. We
know Lowden County, Virginia. We've
heard that 450,000 people 200 day
centers 100 more construction. You take
it from a ratio perspective for every
one day is center that represents 200
2,250 people. So one day center 2250
people right now in Laramie County.
We'll use it from a county perspective.
103,000 people
13 day center is an operational varies
from 121 13 we'll say 13 current ratio
is for every one day center that's 5,147
people if you do 40 one day center
that's 2513
people if it were be to 50 one day
center for a 258 people 60 one day s to
1715 15 70. Okay, I know there's been
talks may not be a number, but let's say
it is 70. One day, ser, 1470 people.
So, our ratio, if we were to go at the
high end, would be higher than Lowden
County, Virginia from a ratio
perspective. Okay, we have to take that
into consideration. That is a very, very
large number. And remember, the ones in
Virginia have been there a long time.
Ones here have not. Remember the ones
two in Virginia, okay? They were smaller
when they started, now they're a lot
bigger. So, we have to take that in
consideration, too. So, I just want to
give those numbers out there. Okay? I
calculated myself. Okay? We have to
really ask, can Cheyen alone sustain it
or be better to have him spread out in
Gillette, in Cody, in Casper, in
Rollins? Okay. To some of the ponder.
Thank you.
>> Thank you. And I did he go away?
Okay, I'm going to close public comment.
So, committee.
Can I get a mo can I get a motion and a
second?
>> So, I uh
>> are you going to
>> I um recommend that this be uh passed on
to the city council itself.
And I make that motion in the light of
experience and uh what we're hearing
here today. It's for the purpose of
discussion.
>> Okay. Uh Mr. Leborn move to um approve.
Is there a second?
Okay. The motion dies for lack of a
second. Uh the recommendation
from the public service committee.
>> There is there is no
>> there will be I'm sorry. There will be
no recommendation to the governing body
at the next meeting of the govern at
next governing body meeting. And that
concludes our agenda for today. So thank
you.